<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The duty and blessing of a tender conscience plainly stated, and earnestly recommended to all that regard acceptance with God, and the prosperity of their souls / by T. Cruso.</title>
            <author>Cruso, Timothy, 1656?-1697.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 149 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 83 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35319</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">8118554</idno>
  <idno type="VID">40873</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248497532</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing C7437</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24287</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">08118554</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35319)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40873)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1227:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The duty and blessing of a tender conscience plainly stated, and earnestly recommended to all that regard acceptance with God, and the prosperity of their souls / by T. Cruso.</title>
                  <author>Cruso, Timothy, 1656?-1697.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 148 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.R. for J. Salusbury,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Conscience.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Christian ethics.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40873:1"/>
            <p>THE DUTY and BLESSING OF A <hi>Tender Conscience:</hi> Plainly Stated, AND Earnestly Recommended To all that regard Acceptance with God, and the Prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of their Souls.</p>
            <p>By <hi>T. Cruso.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Vox Clamantis in Deserto. <hi>Pag.</hi> 44.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Procul à nobis absint non solùm Crimina, sed omnis Criminum Suspitio, &amp; vel prima facies Vitiorum.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. R.</hi> for <hi>I. Salusbury,</hi> at the <hi>Rising Sun</hi> in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> near the <hi>Royal Exchange.</hi> MDCXCI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:40873:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40873:2"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>AS the sad Consideration of the too great and general decay of Serious Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion among a Crowd of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders to it, (which I think, the ensuing Discourses if pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctically digested, might lead and help in some measure to cure) was the chief thing which first engag'd me in the choice of this <hi>Subject,</hi> and is that which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces me now to Publish it; so I am not insensible that the very <hi>Title</hi> which it bears, is enough
<pb facs="tcp:40873:3"/>to expose it to the <hi>Ignorance of foolish men,</hi> and to draw the severest censure upon that which might more naturally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to their conviction. Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of persons are so strong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prejudic't against every <hi>thing</hi> of this kind, which thwarts their Licentious Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and Courses, that the meer sight or sound of the <hi>Name,</hi> will raise their indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and blow up that <hi>wrath of man</hi> which does too power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully obstruct the <hi>working of the Righteousness of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I calmly expect the <hi>casting of flouds out of</hi> such <hi>Mouths,</hi> when I consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
<pb facs="tcp:40873:3"/>that the principal Myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Gospel have been as ill treated, as any thing that I have written here, can be; Who does not know that the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Regeneration and the <hi>Newbirth,</hi> (which is repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented by the Holy Ghost,<note place="margin">Psal. 87.3. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> as one of the <hi>Glorious things spoken of the City of God)</hi> hath been made the matter of Derision, and cavill'd at in a worse manner now, than it was by <hi>Nicodemus</hi> heretofore? And therefore if any of <hi>the Reproaches of Christ</hi> do fall upon these Lines, I shall not onely rest satisfied in it as that which I look't for, but
<pb facs="tcp:40873:4"/>account it a greater mark of <hi>Honour</hi> and Reputation, than the most favourable Sentence from such corrupt and partial Judges would be.</p>
            <p>Nevertheless I venture to say, that I hope better things frm some, particularly from those, who first heard, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards approv'd what is here offer'd to common view;and I hope it indeed the more, the less this performance is adapted to please the fancies of the want only curious. My sincere design in <hi>this,</hi> was the same which I trust I shall ever pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sue in my whole Ministerial Work; viz. <hi>To commend
<pb facs="tcp:40873:4"/>my self to every ones Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science in the sight of God;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.2.</note> as <hi>that</hi> is the faculty which I have been here peculiarly exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis'd about, and indeavour'd to rectify, so I would make <hi>it</hi> the sole Arbiter of what I have done, and readily abide by its determination. If I had taken those methods in the Composure, which suit with the Genius of the present Age, it might per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps have <hi>pleased</hi> a few upon that score, but would have <hi>profited</hi> none; The sayings of Heathen <hi>Orators</hi> and <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sophers</hi> seem to carry more authority with many, than what can be urg'd out of the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:40873:5"/>and <hi>Apostles;</hi> but how little reforming efficacy those fragments of the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture have in comparison of the Dictates of Scripture, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versations of these men for the most part do sufficiently speak.</p>
            <p>And I take leave to add for the quickning of those that make a better Profession, into whose hands Providence may cast this Book, that if it should not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that end of <hi>doing good,</hi> which Ihave framed it to serve, it will besides my intention, have the quite contrary effect of <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing evil:</hi> As every <hi>word</hi> of God shall certainly accomplish something or other, to our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage
<pb facs="tcp:40873:5"/>or our hurt; the like may be said of all <hi>Writings</hi> of this nature too; if a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and diligent improvement be made, it may give occasion of everlasting praise and thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness in <hi>Heaven;</hi> but if after a sleight and cursory perusal, any should imagine that the work is done, and the purpose answer'd, without the least re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution form'd, or endeavour us'd, to regulate their future practice, it will tend to aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate the torment of self-reflex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions in <hi>Hell.</hi> I humbly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat therefore every one, as I solemnly charge my self, to look upon these things not as <hi>Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:40873:6"/>to be onely lodg'd in the Mind, but as <hi>Rules</hi> to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served in the Life; seconding this Injunction and Request with my hearty Prayers to the <hi>God of all Grace,</hi> that such lively impressions of the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Truths may be made upon the Hearts both of <hi>Author,</hi> and <hi>Readers,</hi> as effectually to prevent their <hi>rising up in Judgment</hi> against the one or the other.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. C.</signed>
               <date>
                  <hi>May 4. 1691.</hi>
               </date>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:40873:6"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Duty</hi> and <hi>Blessing</hi> OF A Tender CONSCIENCE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 Kin. 22.19. first clause.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Because thy Heart was ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, —</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Excellent Person whom these words con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, was one of the <hi>best</hi> of the Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi> and the <hi>youngest</hi> who ever sat upon that Throne, being but eight
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:40873:7"/>years old, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">ver. </seg>1</label> when he began to Reign. God had much work for him to do, and therefore brought him to the Government betimes. About three hundred years before, (as some compute) even in the dayes of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> when the Kingdoms of <hi>Israel</hi> and <hi>Judah</hi> were first divided, he was spoken of <hi>by name,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings 13.2.</note> as a Prince that should be a zealous Reformer. In the eighth year of his Reign, (and sixteenth of his Life) he gave manifest proofs of his <hi>enquiring early after God;</hi> and in the twelfth year of his Reign,<note place="margin">2 Chro. 34.3.</note> he vigorously set about the purging of the Land, and abolishing of Idols. When he came to his eighteenth year, he applyed himself to the repairing of the Temple,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Kings 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.5.</note> in which work nothing remarkable had been done since the dayes of <hi>Jehoash.</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:40873:7"/>He now sends his principal Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of State to <hi>Hilkiah</hi> the High-Priest, with necessary orders for this purpose, and while they who had the oversight of this affair were searching among the Ruines, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">ver. </seg>8</label> the <hi>Original Book</hi> of the Law written by <hi>Moses</hi> was Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videntially found.</p>
            <p>It is very probable, that some of the preceding Idolatrous Kings had sought to burn all the <hi>Copies</hi> of the Law they could meet with; and therefore that which God had ordered to be <hi>laid up in the side of the Ark,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 31.26.</note> might be taken thence in those persecuting times by some faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Priests, and hid in a more se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret place for the use of Poste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. This valuable Treasure, which had been lost a great while, being now seasonably re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd, and brought to light,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:40873:8"/>was delivered to <hi>Josiah,</hi> who upon the reading of it, immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately <hi>rent his cloathes:</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">ver. </seg>11</label> (which was the outward expression of an extraordinary inward com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion) Some transcripts, or at least some <hi>broken pieces</hi> of this Sacred Volume, 'tis likely had been preserv'd, and come to his view before, or else he would have scarcely done so much, and gone so far as he did; but he was struck with reverence to this most Authentick Book, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps wrought upon the more by those <hi>affecting passages,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lev. 26. Deut. 28.</note> wherein Idolatry is so severely threaten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Huldah</hi> the Prophetess is here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon consulted, what would be the best course to prevent the <hi>Judgment written;</hi> and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of consulting her seems to be intimated in those words;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:40873:8"/>
               <hi>Now she dwelt in Jerusalem in the Colledge.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">ver. </seg>14</label> The King was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry earnest and impatient to be satisfied in the matter, and she was near at hand; whereas <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 1.2.</note> though he enter'd upon his Office five years before, was, it may be, in some remoter part of <hi>Judah,</hi> and possibly, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued yet at <hi>Anathoth,</hi> his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Town, where we read, that he Prophesyed,<note place="margin">c. 11.21.</note> till they <hi>sought his life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Answer which <hi>Huldah</hi> sent back, referr'd partly to the People, and partly to <hi>Josiah</hi> himself. 1. To the <hi>People</hi> of the Land; letting them know,<note place="margin">ver. 15.16, 17.</note> that they should fall under the Calamities which God had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced in his Law, because of their former open Provocations, and their present feigned Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; for even now, though
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:40873:9"/>they were animated by a pious Governour,<note place="margin">Jer. 3.10.</note> they <hi>returned not unto God with ther whole hearts.</hi> 2. What related to the <hi>King,</hi> was more comfortable and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging; (as will appear in the progress of this Discourse;) he being of <hi>another Spirit,</hi> very differing from his degenerate Subjects; which is here set forth at the very beginning of that part of the Message, <hi>Because thy Heart was Tender,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>That by the <hi>Heart</hi> in this place, the <hi>Conscience</hi> is especially meant, is too plain to need any laborious proof, and therefore the promiscuous use of those words will require no studied Apology. The Scripture does abundantly justify such an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation; as to which, two instances onely shall be given <hi>Solomon</hi> told <hi>Shimei,</hi> that he <hi>knew
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40873:9"/>all the wickedness which his heart was privy to,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings 2.44.</note>
               <hi>which he did to David his father; i. e.</hi> his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science could not but witness against him, the Curses and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilings which his Mouth had ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd. So the <hi>Beloved Apostle</hi> speaks of the <hi>Heart condemning,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 3.20, 21.</note> and <hi>not condemning;</hi> which must be understood of the Judgment which Conscience passes, either for, or against us.</p>
            <p>The main Doctrinal <hi>Observa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> which the words offer to us,<note place="margin">Obs.</note> is this, that <hi>Holy Tenderness of Heart is such a frame and dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition, as God highly approves and rewards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In handling which, I propose this Method. To shew
<list>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:40873:10"/>
                  <item>I. What are the Counterfeits of it.</item>
                  <item>II. What is the true Principle up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which 'tis founded.</item>
                  <item>III. What are its proper Ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents.</item>
                  <item>IV. What are the Means which help towards it.</item>
                  <item>V. What are the Tokens and Evidences whereby it is disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd.</item>
                  <item>VI. Wherein does its Pleasingess to God appear.</item>
                  <item>VII. Why does it find such Accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with him.</item>
                  <item>VIII. Apply it.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> To shew, what are the deceiving <hi>Counterfeits</hi> of this blessed frame. There are Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of two kinds, which the Devil sets up in the room of it: In shaping the one he comes very
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:40873:10"/>
               <hi>short,</hi> in the other he strives, as it were, to <hi>exceed</hi> the real Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Temper. Sometimes it is <hi>shrunk</hi> below its due and neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary proporting, at other times it is <hi>stretcht</hi> too far. On both hands the Errour is mischievous, but especially that which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sists in <hi>Defect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>First, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> Men may be too often deluded with Counterfeits of this Grace, which do not <hi>come up to the truth</hi> of it. As in the following particulars.</p>
            <p>There is a <hi>softness of Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution</hi> which is sometimes mista<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for holy Tenderness; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> and this shews it self two wayes, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by a compassionate regard to the miseries and distresses, or by a forward compliance with the suggestions and perswasions of others.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:40873:11"/> 1. There is a common <hi>pity and compassion,</hi> with respect to the calamities of other persons, which may sometimes in a more than ordinary measure break forth from the unsanctified. All wicked men are not such <hi>Nabals,</hi> as to be stript of Humanity; and <hi>Humanity</hi> in an eminent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree does too often pass for <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianity,</hi> with those who discern not between <hi>things that differ.</hi> Multitudes <hi>put on Bowels</hi> to them that are in distress, whose Hearts do still remain <hi>as a ston<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in the matters of God, and their own Salvation; they are great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affected with the sight of <hi>suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering objects,</hi> and yet their <hi>si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> is never <hi>before them;</hi> they are presently <hi>toucht with the feeling of</hi> anothers <hi>infirmities,</hi> but har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den'd against the sense of their <hi>own pollutions. Pharaohs Daughter</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:40873:11"/>when she saw <hi>Moses in the flags,</hi> though she concluded him to be one of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Children, was moved with pity towards him;<note place="margin">Ex. 2.6.</note> and yet we cannot argue from thence, that the <hi>Plague of her Heart</hi> was <hi>heal'd,</hi> any more than her <hi>Fathers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. There is a <hi>readiness of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyance</hi> with what others suggest and perswade us to, which some persons may miscall Tenderness. Such easie tempers are to be found in the World, that melt like <hi>Wax</hi> to every <hi>flame,</hi> and are prepar'd to receive the <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression</hi> of every <hi>Seal.</hi> All Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners are not equally refractory and stubborn; but some will lend an attentive Ear to serious admonitions, and just <hi>when they are instructed,</hi> will <hi>smite upon their thigh,</hi> but these promising appearances come to nothing.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40873:12"/>They seem <hi>flexible</hi> to good, but they will not <hi>stand bent</hi> towards it; they will give their consent to holy motions <hi>for the present,</hi> but when the next Temptation comes, that consent is withdrawn and revok't;<note place="margin">1 Sam. 24.16. with 26.2.</note> as <hi>Saul</hi> seem'd to be convinc't of the Innocence of <hi>David</hi> sometimes, and yet soon after pursued him as a <hi>Traitour.</hi> These very men that are brought over with so little pains to justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie Religion, are also carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way as easily by others to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise contrary to it; they whom we think so much inclin'd to <hi>yield to God,</hi> are as forward to <hi>give place to the Devil;</hi> if they be apt to hearken to the dictates of Christian Friends, they are as prone to <hi>walk in the counsels of the Ʋngodly.</hi> If <hi>Zedekiahs Princes</hi> will have the <hi>Prophet Jeremy</hi> put to death,<note place="margin">Jer. 38.5.</note>
               <hi>He is not
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:40873:12"/>the man that can do any thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is a <hi>formal Humiliation</hi> under the threatening or pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of <hi>approaching ruine,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> which common beholders are apt to think better of than it deserves, being short of that Tenderness which the Holy Ghost does aim at here. When <hi>Ahab</hi> heard the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>errible things, which <hi>Elijah</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ronounc't against him and his House, <hi>he fasted, and lay in sack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>loth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings 21.27.</note>
               <hi>and went softly; i. e.</hi> after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he manner of deep Mourners, whose Spirits are mightily seiz'd with the loss which they bewail. Any one who saw that King of <hi>Israel</hi> in this afflicted posture, would have been ready to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine, that the <hi>Rock</hi> was really <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>truck, and that these were <hi>fruits <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eet for Repentance;</hi> for God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uts the case to the very Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40873:13"/>
               <hi>seest thou how Ahab hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth himself?</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">ver. </seg>29</label> And yet the <hi>sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of Omri were kept</hi> still, and none of the sins were indeed forsaken, for which all that sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row was pretended. Some are so <hi>afraid at Gods tokens,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ps. 65.8.</note> that they instantly fall at his feet, and lye in the dust before him; and if there be any <hi>wickedness in their hands,</hi> they will put it a way from thence, but still it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>sweet in their mouths,</hi> and safe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their bosomes. They that pas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to and fro on the great Waters though little acquainted wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Religion at other times, may b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> quicken'd by danger to some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Devotion, and to see<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> necessity of cleansing from the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> sins:<note place="margin">Job 41.25.</note>
               <hi>By reason of breakings</hi> (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> furious agitations of the Sea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>they purifie themselves.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:40873:13"/>
            <p> There is a meer <hi>legal broken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ess,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> which is the effect of ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le horrour, and a <hi>Spirit of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndage,</hi> whereby men may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eceiv'd and impos'd upon; but <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vangelical Tenderness</hi> is quite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother thing. Some when they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ear, or think of the <hi>words of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is Curse,</hi> and consider how <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>readful</hi> it is to fall into the hands <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God, and to fall under the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rath to come, and yet how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>possible it is in their present <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ourse and condition to escape <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, they are cast into <hi>fits of trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing;</hi> from the <hi>Law</hi> they have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>knowledge of sin</hi> it self, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the dismal consequences of it; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd when they look within, they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lainly apprehend that their own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ase is infinitely hazardous, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> more <hi>for Wrath,</hi> than <hi>for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onscience sake,</hi> sin grows a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle into dislike, only under the
<gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:40873:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:40873:14"/>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:40873:15"/>notion of a pernicious formida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble evil. It is probable enough that <hi>Felix</hi> had not been moved by <hi>Paul's reasoning of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness and Temperance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 24.25.</note> if the Apostle had not inserted that pungent Discourse of a <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to come;</hi> this gave an <hi>edge</hi> to the other parts of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and <hi>cut the Spirit</hi> of the Governour, but it was heal'd again too quickly after. When men are <hi>dissolv'd</hi> by such Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments meerly, their <hi>hardness is not cur'd;</hi> the <hi>work of the Law</hi> is ordinarily necessary in some measure by way of Introducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but <hi>of it self</hi> it is not suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient; the chief <hi>motives of the Gospel,</hi> which must perfect the change, are of another sort.</p>
            <p>There may be a <hi>cautious shun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> of some sins, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> joyn'd with a <hi>consident rushing</hi> upon others,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:40873:15"/>which is no better than a shew of Tenderness; for that which is <hi>true,</hi> is universal. Our Saviour reprov'd the Pharisees,<note place="margin">Mat. 23.24.</note> for <hi>strain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at a Gnat, and swallowing a Camel;</hi> there is indeed a double evil in this. 1. It is a sign of real <hi>Hypocrisie</hi> in the <hi>persons themselves.</hi> 2. It tempts other men to think that <hi>all Religion</hi> is so. This was frequent among the <hi>Jews;</hi> they would quietly omit the <hi>weightier matters</hi> of the Law, and rigorously insist upon the <hi>lesser.</hi> They would not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect the paying of <hi>Tithes</hi> for the <hi>smallest Herbs</hi> in their own Gardens, and yet could <hi>devour Widows houses</hi> without remorse. They exclaim'd against the Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples for <hi>gathering a few ears of corn on the Sabbath day,</hi> when their whole Religion ran up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>barren stalk</hi> and <hi>empty
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:40873:16"/>blade</hi> of an external Profession. They thought it a crime not to <hi>garnish the Tombs of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> and yet counted it none to <hi>kill the Lord of Life.</hi> They boggled not at the <hi>giving</hi> of Money to <hi>betray innocent Bloud,</hi>
               <note place="margin">c. 27.6.</note> but were against the <hi>receiving</hi> of it, when the desperate wretch whom they had hir'd, came and threw it back. So, <hi>Herod</hi> was very shy of violating his <hi>Oath</hi> to a lascivious Damsel, but too re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute in the beheading of a <hi>just man and an holy.</hi> Nay, the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God also have been sometimes too remiss and faulty in this point, which hath ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misht them more than any thing besides. <hi>Bathshebah</hi> took care to <hi>purifie her self</hi> from a <hi>Ceremonial uncleanness,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 11.4.</note> and yet did not start at a <hi>Moral pollution.</hi> Yea, it would have been well, if <hi>Davids
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:40873:16"/>heart had smote him</hi> assoon after his <hi>Adultery</hi> and <hi>Murder,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 24.5. 2 Sam. 24.10.</note> as it did after the <hi>cutting of Sauls skirt,</hi> and his <hi>numbering of the people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There may be a <hi>strict forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> of the visible and <hi>open acts</hi> of sin, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> and yet no such tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness wrought in the Heart, as there ought to be. Common restraints, or the care of a Mans Reputation or Worldly Interest, may influence him to this, and yet he may not have the least tincture of <hi>godly fear.</hi> Whoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever does secretly harbour sin, he hath the <hi>spot of the Devils Children,</hi> though he do not pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly commit it; as <hi>Rachel,</hi> when she <hi>sat upon the Images</hi> to conceal them, was scarcely more innocent, than if she had been making a <hi>Religious use</hi> of them. If the <hi>Church</hi> could not have
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:40873:17"/>purg'd her self from that guilt which God will <hi>search out,</hi> as well as from that which men might perceive, the profession of her uprightness might have been easily contradicted; but as their <hi>steps had not declined from Gods way,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 44.18.</note> so their <hi>hearts were not turned back.</hi> Counterfeit tenderness looks no further than the regulating and forming of the outward actions according to the Word of God, while the inward thoughts and affections are permitted to take their own unbridled course. The <hi>remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance</hi> of sin is pleasant to such, though the <hi>practice</hi> be uneasy; they <hi>rowl it under their Tongue,</hi> though they dare not bring it forth; they avoid (it may be) the staining of their <hi>Conversati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> but regard not the defiling of their <hi>Consciences.</hi> For the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:40873:17"/>affronting and dishonouring of <hi>God</hi> is not so much to them, as the blasting or diminishing of <hi>their own good name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> It is possible that men may be cheated and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd by Satan, under the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of necessary tenderness, with those things on the <hi>other hand,</hi> which are <hi>carried beyond</hi> all just and reasonable bounds. As particularly,</p>
            <p>This tenderness which the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God commends, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> is not an <hi>affection</hi> of being <hi>righteous o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vermuch;</hi> I mean, of exceeding the Commands of God, and a pretending to greater strictness than is enjoyn'd. This is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally of very mischievous conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence; from one extream men soon run to another, from <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commanded severities,</hi> to <hi>forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:40873:18"/>licentiousness:</hi> They <hi>screw up</hi> the Precept farther than God design'd it, and instead of keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it at that <hi>height,</hi> they noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously <hi>break</hi> it. When men fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sten their own additions to the Word, and think to be Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>above what is written,</hi> the Devil hath the greatest advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of thrusting them down in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Prophaneness. Duty is to be done <hi>with all our might,</hi> but the declared will of God is the measure and standard of Duty. If we enlarge our own task, and <hi>increase our own burden,</hi> that's the way to neglect and <hi>shake off all.</hi> We should therefore see that we do not <hi>make</hi> Duties or Sins, where God hath made <hi>none,</hi> lest we come to <hi>reckon</hi> those things <hi>as no</hi> Duties or Sins, which are <hi>truly so.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:40873:18"/>
            <p> It is not a <hi>troubling</hi> or <hi>tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting</hi> of our selves with <hi>fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volous and groundless Scruples,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and so living in melancholly bondage all our dayes. This may be indeed an indication of Grace, but yet 'tis an <hi>Infirmity,</hi> like the <hi>tenderness of Leahs eyes,</hi> and makes the Soul to <hi>refuse that comfort</hi> and satisfaction, which it ought to receive. At this rate, Conscience must alwayes be <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved far from Peace,</hi> and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry trifle, yea every nothing, will give us as much disturbance, as the most terrifying reality. <hi>Fearing</hi> to offend, where <hi>no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of fear is,</hi> must needs be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted rather an instance of weakness, than perfection. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> had a rebuke for <hi>calling that unclean, which God had cleansed;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts. 10.15.</note> and no man is to be commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the puzzling and perplex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:40873:19"/>of himself, when the <hi>case is so plain,</hi> that 'tis onely his <hi>own perplexity which obscures</hi> it. What is this, but to <hi>stumble upon eaven ground,</hi> or chuse to <hi>walk in pain,</hi> like the Traveller with a Stone in his Shooe, when he ought ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to sit down, and endeavour the taking of it out? God does no where put us upon flying from <hi>shaken leaves,</hi> or turning innocent things into <hi>grieving thorus,</hi> and <hi>piercing swords;</hi> he that does so, imbitters his Life through his own folly; for a man may spend all his years <hi>upon the rack,</hi> if he will indulge eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry dark imagination that rises up in his Mind. That Rule of the Apostle is of a larger extent, than the single Case, which i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was laid down for;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.25.</note>
               <hi>Whatsoever is sold in the shambles, that eat asking no question for conscience sake.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:40873:19"/>
            <p> It is not a yielding to any such <hi>doubts</hi> as would deterr and <hi>hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der us from the Service of God,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and Communion with him. This is not the work of the Spirit, but one of the <hi>wiles of the Devil,</hi> to put us out of our main busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and to rob us of our choic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est priviledge. It may be, he raises a Question in some droop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Souls, that have been long exercised with his Temptations, and <hi>buffeted by his Messengers,</hi> Whether it were not better to <hi>intermit</hi> those acts of Worship, in which they must acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge so great a mixture of sin? He would perswade some, that the irreverent or <hi>blasphemous Thoughts,</hi> which are perhaps in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected into Minds in <hi>Prayer,</hi> is an argument against the bowing of their Knees; or that the <hi>wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derings and distractions</hi> of their
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:40873:20"/>Spirits in <hi>Hearing,</hi> through pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent multiplicity of Secular Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, is a reason why they should keep their foot from going to the House of God; or that <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest unworthiness,</hi> and <hi>want of</hi> desir'd <hi>assurance</hi> are sufficient <hi>bars to the Lords Table.</hi> These things, by Satans management, often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times do either <hi>wholly obstruct</hi> the performance of such Duties, or they make the <hi>Knees</hi> very <hi>feeble</hi> in them, and the <hi>Hands</hi> to <hi>bang down;</hi> they take away much of the <hi>Heart,</hi> if they do not shut out the <hi>Service.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude therefore, that it is no branch of due Tenderness to call this point into dispute, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be <hi>good for us to draw nigh to God?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 73.28.</note>
            </p>
            <p>An <hi>extraordinary sensible com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punction</hi> in all persons at all times, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> is not absolutely requisite to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:40873:20"/>Tenderness As all have not equal <hi>strength of Grace,</hi> so all have not equal <hi>stock of Moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sture;</hi> not the same command ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther over <hi>Natural Passions,</hi> or <hi>Bodily Humours.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Tho. Manton</hi> on Psal. 119.136.</note> A Dry Brain (sayes a Great Author) may fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently be matcht with a Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Heart. I deny not, but that where this <hi>Water</hi> is, 'tis fit that it should be <hi>drawn</hi> and <hi>pour'd out before the Lord:</hi> God testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies of <hi>Josiah</hi> in the Text, that he <hi>wept before him;</hi> and <hi>David</hi> sayes,<note place="margin">Psal. 6.6. Acts 20.19. 2 Cor. 2.4.</note> that he <hi>watered his couch with his tears, and made his bed to swim</hi> with them; and <hi>Paul</hi> could seldom <hi>Preach</hi> or <hi>Write</hi> without <hi>many</hi> of them; but these are not to be drawn into such binding Examples, as if e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one that attained not the same which they did, must be blotted out of the Roll of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:40873:21"/>Christians. I doubt not, but that many Hypocrites in the World <hi>out-do</hi> many real Saints in such external things: The <hi>Eye</hi> of a wretched deceiver may be an <hi>overflowing fountain,</hi> when the upright Soul is much more <hi>straiten'd</hi> in the expressing of it self after that manner. <hi>Hard hearts</hi> may <hi>weep,</hi> when the <hi>soft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est</hi> may not; as the solid <hi>pave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> at some seasons of the year may be <hi>wet,</hi> when the gentler <hi>hangings</hi> discover no such change. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/>
            </p>
            <p>This tenderness does not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige us to a renouncing or <hi>laying aside of all prudence</hi> and discre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the choice of the <hi>most important</hi> Duties, when there is a <hi>competition</hi> of more than one at the same time. A Tender Heart should urge no man un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advisedly to engage in a <hi>lesser
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:40873:21"/>duty,</hi> when a <hi>greater</hi> offers it self. There ought to be an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise of judgment, in consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, when there are divers calls, what God does most probably call to <hi>at the present time;</hi> and in weighing the circumstances of things, that we may do that which will be <hi>most acceptable and useful,</hi> though we leave other matters undone. It is true, that <hi>no</hi> good works are to be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully omitted, nor put off and suspended, unless necessity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire: We are bound to do <hi>all</hi> that is commanded, and <hi>when</hi> it is commanded:<note place="margin">Ps. 27.8.</note>
               <hi>When thou said<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est, seek ye my face, my heart said unto thee,</hi> &amp;c. but sometimes one Duty is <hi>supplanted</hi> by another, through the disposal of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, without any agency of ours; and the <hi>preference</hi> of one Duty to another becomes inevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:40873:22"/>and if we study the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Duties well, it will not appear any unequal thing. <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stituted</hi> Duties ought to give way to <hi>Moral</hi> ones, when they meet one another; 'tis a blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able tenderness, when men will rather forbear an <hi>act of Mercy,</hi> than set aside the <hi>offering of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice,</hi> or rather let alone a <hi>work of Charity,</hi> than perform it <hi>on the Sabbath day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> To shew what is the true <hi>principle and foundation</hi> which a Tender Heat is built upon. The <hi>summary Answer</hi> might be; <hi>Deep Conviction and sound Conversion wrought and maintained by God.</hi> This Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter given to <hi>JOsiah</hi> cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to any unconvinced or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>converted person in the World <hi>i. e.</hi> it can belong to none, but
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:40873:22"/>what have come, and do conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, under the mighty Operati\on of God. But to open tis more distinctly;</p>
            <p>First, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Tenderness of Heart supposes <hi>deep conviction,</hi> as that which must go before, in order to the producing of such a frame. The <hi>sword in Christs mouth</hi> must <hi>pierce</hi> (as it were) <hi>between the joynts and the marrow, divide the soul and spirit asunder,</hi> and make such kind of <hi>wounds,</hi> as the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardless sinner never felt before.<note place="margin">Acts 2.37.</note>
               <hi>When they heard this they were pricked in their heart, and said unto Peter and the rest of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles, men and brethren, what shall we do?</hi> Where the word does not <hi>enter</hi> thus, the Heart will remain hard still, and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully insensible both of Sin and Duty. A <hi>sound</hi> which only passes by the <hi>Ear,</hi> signifies no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:40873:23"/>more than a <hi>feather drawn over the Skin,</hi> till the <hi>Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment comes</hi> with power, for the raising of mens stupid faculties out of their <hi>dead sleep. Christ</hi> told <hi>Judas</hi> the he <hi>had a Devil,</hi> and <hi>would betray him,</hi> yet Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science never stir'd, so as to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute its office to any purpose.</p>
            <p>So long as men are <hi>alive</hi> and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous, chearful and confident, (as <hi>Paul</hi> was once in his natural condition) <hi>without the Law,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 7.9.</note> this disposition of holy tenderness is not likely to spring up in them; and men may be truly said to be without the Law, though they have the outward dispensation of it, so long as they are not throughly convinc'd and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled by it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> It supposes a <hi>sound conversion;</hi> a real change of state and temper, an entire transfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:40873:23"/>of the man into a <hi>new creature:</hi> This is the meaning of that excellent promise in the <hi>New Covenant;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 11.19.</note>
               <hi>I will take out the sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny heart,</hi> (<hi>q. d.</hi> I will <hi>break</hi> that to pieces by the <hi>hammer</hi> of my Word) <hi>and will give them an heart of flesh.</hi> Here is an Heart <hi>instead</hi> of an Heart; the quality of it so much alter'd from what it was, that it is perfectly ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. It is like a <hi>turning of dry ground</hi> (as the <hi>Psalmist</hi> speaks) <hi>into water-springs;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 107.35.</note> or a turning of <hi>Rocks</hi> into <hi>Rivers,</hi> the most firm and impenetrable substances into those which are most fluid and yielding. The maddest <hi>mirth</hi> is chang'd into the most afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>sorrow;</hi> the most <hi>undaunted sinning</hi> into the most <hi>penitent consussion;</hi> that will which was like an <hi>Iron sinew,</hi> and stood stiff against the authority of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:40873:24"/>God, is now most <hi>pliable</hi> and submissive to it; those affection which were set upon the vile<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lusts, and taken off from God are now alienated as much from <hi>them,</hi> and linkt as closely to <hi>him</hi> Such a <hi>renewing of the mind</hi> there must be, a destroying of old ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits, and a planting of contrary ones, if ever the Heart be truly tender.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> It supposes this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction and Conversion to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>wrought by God.</hi> Such <hi>high moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains,</hi> as our Hearts naturally are, (like vast <hi>heaps of filth cas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> up in the way of the Lord</hi>) wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> not <hi>flow down</hi> at any <hi>presence</hi> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>his.</hi> None is able <hi>of these stone to raise up</hi> believing <hi>Children,</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Spiritual Seed, to <hi>Abraham,</hi> but only he. He against whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is committed, must give savin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Repentance for sin; he that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:40873:24"/>
               <hi>pressed under us</hi> Metaphorically, must cause us to <hi>feel the load</hi> of our own defilements really; the God in <hi>whose sight</hi> we are most <hi>abominable,</hi> must bring us to <hi>loath our selves.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 21.1.</note> He <hi>fashioned the heart</hi> at first, and he can <hi>turn it which way he pleases:</hi> It was formed by his hand originally, and it is in his hand still; <hi>i. e.</hi> it is under his soveraign power, which he can successfully exert in any case. It is his work to incline and <hi>bow</hi> the hearts of men, to things, from which they were most a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse; (as the <hi>men of Judah</hi> who had stuck out so long,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 19.14.</note> were made unanimously to concurr in the invitation of <hi>David</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn home to his People;) and a secret invisible <hi>touch</hi> of his will be effectual in this case; (so it was with respect to that <hi>band of men,</hi> that went with <hi>Saul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 10.26.</note> after
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:40873:25"/>he was chosen;) as the diseased woman in the Gospel, said with in her self,<note place="margin">Mat. 9.21</note>
               <hi>If I may but touch hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Garment, I shall be whole.</hi> The <hi>weakest communication</hi> from God excells the <hi>strongest reasonings</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> men. He can operate upon the roughest Natures; make a stur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> dy <hi>Goaler</hi> to <hi>tremble</hi> before h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Prisoners,<note place="margin">Acts 16.29.</note> and <hi>wash their stripes</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> It supposes, that what <hi>hath been</hi> wrought by God <hi>is yet maintained</hi> by him. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> upholding of this frame princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally depends upon the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed influence of the Grace o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God every moment after its <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> production; and if those influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences were stopt, the greates<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> tenderness would <hi>degenerate</hi> inter worse hardness, than we labou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> under, as we come into th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> World. Souls that had bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> once <hi>thawed</hi> would <hi>freeze</hi> against
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:40873:25"/>into a <hi>thicker ice,</hi> notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the best of humane endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to prevent it. That <hi>ground</hi> which hath been made <hi>good,</hi> and <hi>broken up,</hi> as it ought to be, would quickly prove as bad as the <hi>stony</hi> in the Parable, if not daily <hi>mellowed with the showers</hi> of Heaven, and <hi>distilling dews</hi> of the Blessed Spirit. <hi>The Earth which brings forth herbs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 6.7.</note> is said to <hi>drink in the rain which cometh oft upon it.</hi> Hence it is, that many <hi>degrees</hi> of this holy ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derness are <hi>lost,</hi> even in those that are converted, when God does but <hi>take away his Spirit</hi> in part from them; and sin does never so <hi>easily befet them,</hi> nor temptation with so little difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty overcome them, as at those times.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:40873:26"/>
            <p> The <hi>third</hi> thing, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> is to shew What are the proper <hi>Ingredient,</hi> which <hi>constitute</hi> and make up this tenderness of heart. There are four things, in the connexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whereof, this holy Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion here spoken of, does seen to lye.</p>
            <p>First, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <hi>Hatred of sin.</hi> He who is not brought to <hi>abhor that which is evil,</hi> will not be so <hi>cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious</hi> of it as he should be. While sin is the object of desire, a man will be more studious to <hi>comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> it, than to <hi>escape</hi> it; it is much more likely that he should watch and seek <hi>for</hi> opportunities, that resolve or strive <hi>against</hi> them An Heart that's tender in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Scripture-sense, must be fill'd with an holy indignation against every thing that's contrary unto God;<note place="margin">Gen. 39.9.</note> as <hi>Joseph</hi> cryed out, <hi>Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:40873:26"/>can I do this great wickedness, and sin against God?</hi> He could do nothing <hi>willingly,</hi> but what he could do <hi>lawfully;</hi> there was a <hi>Divine Antipathy</hi> in his New Nature to any known impurity. As we are told, that <hi>he who is born of God, cannot sin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 John 3.9.</note>
               <hi>because he is born of God;</hi> deliberate allowed sin is against the very complexion and tendency of his Soul, as it is now settled by Grace; he perfectly detests it, and <hi>therefore</hi> declines it. And indeed this is a more infallible test of a mans integrity, than the meer <hi>not sinning,</hi> taken by it self; for a <hi>wicked man never hates</hi> the evils which he <hi>forbears to do;</hi> a <hi>good man</hi> may be some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>hurried to do</hi> the evils which <hi>indeed he hates.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 7.15.</note> Sin is more loathsome to the Saint that <hi>accidentally commits</hi> it, than to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:40873:27"/>the Sinner who for other <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign reasons avoids</hi> it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <hi>Love of Holiness,</hi> No man but he that delights in good, will be duely tender as to sinful Omissions. Men will be glad of Excuses, when they take no pleasure in the work. If Religious Exercises are not matter of delight, they will <hi>find out many inventions</hi> to stop the mouth of Conscience in laying them aside. Unless we <hi>come,</hi> (as our Lord did, with a spontane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous chearfulness) <hi>to do the will o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God,</hi> it will be no strange thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to see it often left <hi>undone.</hi> Where <hi>Christ</hi> commanded his Hearers to <hi>pray, that their flight</hi> (in the do struction which he threaten'd to <hi>Jerusalem</hi>) <hi>might not be on th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sabbath-day;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 24.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> he seems to inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, that though it were <hi>no unlawful</hi> in a case of extremity
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:40873:27"/>to make their escape upon that day, yet the Sabbath was to be so great a <hi>delight,</hi> that such an hinderance of enjoying it should be <hi>grievous</hi> to them: Spiritual Priviledges and Duties ought to be so much more pleasant and valuable to us, than our Natural Lives. The Wise Man gives us a charge, to <hi>keep the Law,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 7.2.</note>
               <hi>as the Apple of our Eye,</hi> which is one of the tenderest and choic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est parts in the Humane Body; which men naturally take a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar care to guard, because Sight, whereof it is the Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is the noblest Sense. God expresses his love to his people, by bestowing this character up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them;<note place="margin">Zech. 2.8</note>
               <hi>He that toucheth you</hi> (sayes the Prophet to the Church) <hi>toucheth the apple of his Eye;</hi> so should our love be to the ways of God, or else devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:40873:28"/>and diversions from them, will not much affect us.</p>
            <p>Thirdly <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
               <hi>Fear of God.</hi> This planted in the Soul, must be the <hi>bridle</hi> to hold us in, when cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Nature is ready to break out; this must fortify and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure against temptations, when indwelling sin would betray and expose us to them.<note place="margin">Psal. 4.4.</note>
               <hi>Stand in awe and sin not.</hi> This awe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferrs more to the <hi>precepts,</hi> than <hi>threatenings</hi> of the Word; while an <hi>impentient heart</hi> may be <hi>afraid of Divine Judgments,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 13.13.</note> the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der heart is to <hi>fear the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> There is a vast difference between the fear of punishment and the fear of offending; the fear of coming under the <hi>lash of Gods vengeance,</hi> and the fear <hi>of provoking the eyes of his glory.</hi> It is this latter, which is the genu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine Filial Fear; a <hi>Spirit of Fear</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:40873:28"/>not only consistent with a <hi>Spirit of Adoption,</hi> but even proper to those, who <hi>call on the Father,</hi> as such. <hi>Devils tremble,</hi> and yet boldly adventure upon sin; <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,</hi> confirm'd in their holy state,<note place="margin">Jude 9.</note>
               <hi>dare not</hi> do any thing unsuitable to their spotless Nature, or of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fensive to the Majesty whom they attend upon. When our Souls are become like <hi>fleshly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,</hi> for the Righteous Law to be <hi>stampt</hi> and <hi>engraven</hi> on, the very thoughts of displeasing the Maker of that Law will be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to keep us back from breaking it, though there were no penalties annexed to it. They that have <hi>received a kingdom which cannot be moved,</hi> (in title, and in hope) <hi>serve God with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verential fear,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12.28.</note> though not with that which is distrustful and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting; they doubt not their
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:40873:29"/>
               <hi>Reward,</hi> but yet take heed to approve themselves to their <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warder.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
               <hi>Jealousy of our selves.</hi> A tender heart is very inquisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and watchful, that it may not be mistaken in its own state. This is stiled by the Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> a <hi>Godly jealousy:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 11.2.</note> 'Tis necessary to persons <hi>professing Godliness,</hi> and 'tis useful in the <hi>exercising of themselves to it;</hi> 'tis a Godly jealousy, in opposition to <hi>wicked security,</hi> and careless presumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. So long as we <hi>trust in our own hearts,</hi> and build up vair confidences upon sandy bottoms we shall never arrive to that <hi>softness,</hi> which must commend <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to God, and preserve us from the snares of Satan.<note place="margin">2 Tim. 6.19.</note>
               <hi>Laying up in store for our selves a good foundation against the time to come</hi> must be our great design, and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:40873:29"/>diligent endeavour: And seeing there are so many <hi>false founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> which we are sollicited to lay, this plainly includes, that we should be often seriously ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amining, whether ours which we have chosen, be sound or no. If the <hi>heart</hi> by nature be <hi>deceitful above all things,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 17.9.</note> (so that nothing in the world can paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel its treachery) an heart molli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by Grace, will above all things look to this, that it be not <hi>actually deceiv'd.</hi> A truly <hi>contrite Spirit</hi> will be daily searching into it self, that it may be found a <hi>Spirit without guile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>fourth</hi> thing, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> is to shew, what are the <hi>means,</hi> which by divine management, <hi>help towards</hi> such a frame in us. (What course <hi>we</hi> are to take, and what me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:40873:30"/>
               <hi>we</hi> are to use, shall be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards consider'd; but here I would open, how God is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed most usually to bring this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout in <hi>his Dispensations.</hi>) There are four things which occur most remarkable here.</p>
            <p>First, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <hi>Providential warnings.</hi> God many times by <hi>visiting sin upon others</hi> in his Childrens sight, gives a seasonable and happy Allarm to them; he <hi>strikes</hi> their Neighbour, that they may <hi>feel</hi> It was the express <hi>reason</hi> of the execution of many <hi>Judicia Laws</hi> among the <hi>Jews,</hi> upon ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital Offenders,<note place="margin">Deut. 17.13.</note>
               <hi>that all Israel might hear and fear, and do no more presumptuously.</hi> The hopes of Impunity lurking in the heart have a strange influence in the debauching and perverting o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it; but when we see Judgment <hi>come so near</hi> to us, as to seize up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:40873:30"/>him that <hi>stands by</hi> us, the root of that temptation is very much torn and loosen'd. When <hi>Joabs field was set on fire,</hi> tho' the flame did not reach his <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 14.30, 31.</note> he quickly went to <hi>Absalom</hi> to know the meaning of it; so the severity of God <hi>hovering</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout us, though it does not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually <hi>touch</hi> us, may be sanctified to the reviving of those holy im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions on the Soul, which had been too much worn out by the <hi>deceitfulness of sin.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 34.26.</note> Gods <hi>smit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of wicked men in the open view of others,</hi> though it be an aggravation of their punishment, is very often an act of Mercy to those that behold it. Persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Saints are a <hi>spectacle of scorn</hi> to the World, but the condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed World are made a <hi>sign for the admonition</hi> of the Saints. God does in effect say, <q>Thus you
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:40873:31"/>must look that I should deal with you, if this do not quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en you to <hi>be zealous and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent;</hi> the same, or worse Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities are in store for you, if the examples of these sufferers do not make sin more odious and uneasy to you.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <hi>Personal Correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> God knows, that there is a necessity sometimes of using <hi>sharpness</hi> with his own, to bring them to their <hi>right mind,</hi> and kep them in it. Though there is a great unlikeness between the case of <hi>good</hi> and <hi>bad</hi> men in this particular; as there are very manifest <hi>degrees of hardness</hi> in Natural things; and as <hi>short slumbers</hi> do differ from the <hi>spirit of</hi> a <hi>deep sleep.</hi> Bad men are scarcely awaken'd but by some amazing stroke, or by the <hi>thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Gods Power,</hi> as men in a
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:40873:31"/>
               <hi>Lethargy</hi> are not rows'd without some more than ordinary noise; whereas good men are wrought upon by more <hi>ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> means. It must be the tormenting sting of some <hi>deadly Scorpion</hi> which reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers any sense in the one, but the smart of a <hi>Rod</hi> will be suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, through Grace, to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And <hi>so much</hi> we find by many instances, is both proper and needful; for God <hi>beats</hi> with <hi>few</hi> or with <hi>many stripes,</hi> as he sees occasion; he throws us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an <hi>hotter</hi> or <hi>cooler Furnace,</hi> according as we have more or less need of <hi>melting.</hi> He does not delight in <hi>causing his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> (as some <hi>barbarous Idolaters</hi> did theirs) to <hi>pass through the fire,</hi> but when the case requires it, he <hi>performs his work</hi> upon them by it. <hi>Job,</hi> in his prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; seems to have been swell'd <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:40873:32"/>further'd by Gods with-holding the <hi>joy of his Salvation.</hi> The temporary loss of <hi>Comfort</hi> is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times very gainful in respect of <hi>Holiness.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
               <hi>Sinful Miscarriages.</hi> God would not permit such things, if he did not <hi>design</hi> to over-rule them to his own Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and the good of his Servants, and if they were not <hi>capable</hi> of being so over-rul'd. When God hath put Life into us, and <hi>set us upon our feet,</hi> he would prevent our <hi>falling again,</hi> if those very falls, however evil in themselves, could not be so manag'd by him, as to bring about the most ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent contrary ends. Therefore he that hath <hi>stumbled most foul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> is thereby excited afterwards to <hi>walk the more foftly;</hi> and the man that hath been betrary'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to more than ordinary sins since
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:40873:32"/>his Conversion, by prevailing reliques of Corruption, will be the more diligent to guard and <hi>keep himelf</hi> for the time to come,<note place="margin">1 John 5.18.</note>
               <hi>that the wicked one may not touch him. Bruised parts,</hi> we know, use to be more <hi>tender</hi> than any others, and <hi>broken Bones</hi> (tho' restor'd and set again) will be frequent remembrances of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer hurts, and provoke such as have them, to <hi>look well to their goings.</hi> The same <hi>Peter,</hi> who had disown'd and abjur'd his Master, through shameful <hi>cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erdice,</hi> before a company of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants and inferiour persons, sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naliz'd himself, after this, by his <hi>boldness,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.13.</note> before the Rulers of the People; 'tis likely, that his Courage in the <hi>Confession</hi> of Christ now, was rais'd by the thoughts of his former lamented <hi>renunciation;</hi> he that had said,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:40873:33"/>in answer to single challenges, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>know not the man,</hi> now cryes ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Be it known to you all,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">ver. </seg>10</label>
               <hi>that b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the name of Jesus Christ of N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zareth, whom ye crucified,</hi> &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Past Neglects</hi> tend to make me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> more sensible of their obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to <hi>present Duties;</hi> and wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Gods Servants have <hi>slipt</hi> mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> notoriously, they learn to <hi>orde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their steps</hi> the most exactly. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Jews</hi> at this day <hi>flee from Idolatry,</hi> and will not swallow the least <hi>dust of the Golden Cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> by which they heretofore tran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grest, and thereupon are preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dic'd by <hi>Popery</hi> against <hi>Christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity;</hi> so it is with sincere Believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in all other cases. If any on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hath wounded himself by <hi>run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning upon the edge</hi> of the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Commandment,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.10.</note> that very would will be useful to mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> him <hi>chiefly beware of walking after
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:40873:33"/>the flesh in the lust of unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>fifth</hi> Head, is to enquire, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> What are the <hi>Evidences</hi> and To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens whereby this Tenderness is <hi>discoverable.</hi> These are very <hi>nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous;</hi> and therefore instead of multiplying all that I might, I shall contract them into those which follow.</p>
            <p>First, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> A <hi>Zealous Concern for the Honour of God,</hi> when it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terferes, and stands in competi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with <hi>our own;</hi> both in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Faith and Practice. This is an inseparable concomitant, and manifest sign of a Tender Heart. In <hi>matters of Faith,</hi> it makes a great discovery as to this point, when the <hi>Glory of Freegrace</hi> comes to be opposed to our own <hi>Merit,</hi> and the <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness of Christ</hi> to our own
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:40873:34"/>
               <hi>Works,</hi> and the <hi>Efficacy of the Spirit</hi> to our own <hi>Will.</hi> That which <hi>exalts God,</hi> and <hi>vilifyes self</hi> most, will he most grateful to one that hath been duely <hi>hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled</hi> (like <hi>Josiah</hi> here) <hi>before the Lord his God. Paul,</hi> who <hi>fell to the Earth,</hi> when he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, and saw more of his own wretchedness, than thousands do,<note place="margin">Gal. 2.21.</note> was very careful <hi>not to fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate the Grace of God; i. e.</hi> not to represent it as an insigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficant thing, or make it void, by ascribing more than is meet to man. He was quick in <hi>retract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> (as it were) any expression, that might seem to diminish, or entrench upon, the honour of <hi>Christ;</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">ver. </seg>20</label>
               <hi>I live, yet not I, but Christ liveth in me.</hi> So in another place;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.10.</note>
               <hi>I laboured more abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly than they all, yet not I, but the Grace of God, which was with me.</hi>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:40873:34"/>He that will <hi>cloud</hi> the perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances of the Redeemer, or the operations of the Sanctifyer, for the <hi>brightening</hi> of his own, is under an ill symptome. Where the <hi>mystery of Faith is held in a pure Conscience,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.9.</note> men are willing to <hi>decrease</hi> in their Personal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, that their Lords reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue may <hi>increase.</hi> So, in <hi>mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of practice,</hi> Holy Tenderness will make men deny themselves to the very utmost, rather than not advance Gods interest in their places; Sacrifice all their <hi>credit</hi> and esteem, rather than clip his Authority, or mangle his Commands;submit to be counted the <hi>filth of this world,</hi> that they may the better glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie him.</p>
            <p>Secondly, A <hi>strict Endeavour,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> that both the <hi>Ends</hi> which we propose, and the <hi>Means</hi> which
<gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:40873:35"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:40873:35"/>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:40873:36"/>we employ upon all occasions, may be <hi>alike good. Sinful ends</hi> are not to be pursued in the use of the <hi>best means,</hi> nor will the <hi>best ends</hi> consecrate the use of <hi>sinful means.</hi> Corrupt intentions spoil the noblest actions; tho where the <hi>heart is not right,</hi> men only regard the <hi>thing done,</hi> and not the <hi>motive or spring</hi> of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it. It is the <hi>tender heart</hi> which takes care to pluck out the <hi>evil eye;</hi> for if that remains, it will spread and diffuse its malignity into the whole <hi>body</hi> of the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. The <hi>Apostle</hi> complains of some perverse men, that <hi>preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Christ</hi> indeed, (where the act without all doubt, was <hi>materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally</hi> good),<note place="margin">Phil. 1.15, 16.</note> but they did it <hi>out of envy and strife, not sincerely, supposing thereby to add affliction to his bonds:</hi> (So that the aim and design was no better than
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:40873:36"/>
               <hi>Devilish,</hi> while the work was <hi>Angelical.</hi>) On the other side, wicked actions are not excused by the holiest intentions; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God sayes,<note place="margin">Isa. 61.8.</note>
               <hi>I the Lord love judgment, I hate robbery for burnt-offering.</hi> He will not be made the <hi>receiver</hi> of what hath been procur'd by Injustice, nor coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance our application of the effects of Rapine and Oppressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the most Religious or Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable uses. Nothing does more <hi>prophane</hi> the holy name of God, than the <hi>entitling</hi> of him to such vile practises; which an <hi>Anti-christian</hi> Generation hath been very forward to do, <hi>moulding the bread of life into every shape</hi> for their own turn, and crying out, <hi>Here is Christ,</hi> when Satan hath cover'd himself under that Mantle; and by this, as much as any thing, they have justified
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:40873:37"/>that Character,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.2.</note> of <hi>having con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences seared as with an hot iron.</hi> God remembred <hi>Sauls slaying of the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>beonites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 21.2.</note>
               <hi>in his zeal to the children of Israel and Judah,</hi> and revenged it a great while after. And we know, how God cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures the <hi>Princes of Israel,</hi> that they <hi>built up Zion with blood, and Jerusalem with iniquity.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mic. 3.10</note> Such a censure is studiously avoided, if the heart be tender.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> A <hi>vigorous resistance</hi> of the most <hi>plausible and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Temptations.</hi> There is no tryal in this case, when the charm is weak, when the poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son is naked, when the suggesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is unsuitable to our particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar inclination, or when the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luring recompence is small. They must be risen up to a prodigious height of wickedness indeed,<note place="margin">Prov. 28.21.</note> that <hi>will transgress for a piece of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:40873:37"/>bread;</hi> and <hi>sell the</hi> Godly <hi>poor for a pair of shooes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos 2.6.</note> which notes a very contemptible price; but when Temptation comes with a mighty strength, and our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with it is baited with something extraordinary, then our Tenderness is seen, in strug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with, and getting the maste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of, it. Not that it is to be imagin'd, that <hi>every such</hi> Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation shall be successfully with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood, for then it would be pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible, that we might live with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any sin; but <hi>many</hi> instances both of resolute opposition, and final victory may be given, where it hath been most hazar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dous and improbable. As our Lord, with a great deal of holy anger, refus'd the impudent mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>falling down and worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> the Devil, though enforc'd with a prospect and promise of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:40873:38"/>
               <hi>all the Kingdoms of the World:</hi> So his Servants have imitated him in the like resolution, when Satan hath offer'd them very great enticements. <hi>Life</hi> is more to us than all the World, and yet that hath not prevail'd with Christs faithful Souldiers, to <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of deliverance</hi> upon unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful terms.<note place="margin">Heb. 11.35:</note> The Devils best and <hi>choicest Artillery</hi> can do less exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution upon tender hearts, than his <hi>slightest Weapons</hi> against o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> An <hi>impartial shun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of the <hi>smallest sins.</hi> These are wont to be overlookt, and let alone, by the most of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, though greater wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses are severely condemn'd; but indeed, as breaking with God for <hi>a little,</hi> does endanger his delivering of us up to worse and more hainous crimes, so it
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:40873:38"/>argues a vile and wretched con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of God, and unfaithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness to him.<note place="margin">Luke 16.10.</note>
               <hi>He that is unjust in the least, is unjust also in much.</hi> We ought alwayes to consider the greatness of the <hi>person for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding,</hi> more than the aggreva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the <hi>thing forbidden:</hi> (As for Example; <hi>Who</hi> it is that sayes, <hi>Thou shalt not steal,</hi> rather than <hi>what,</hi> or <hi>how much</hi> it is, which we are tempted to the stealing of.) And if our hearts are endued with that tenderness which becomes them, we shall do so. This will provoke us not only to avoid the <hi>flames</hi> of Lust, but the very <hi>sparks,</hi> that we may be not only not <hi>consu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed,</hi> but not so much as <hi>singed,</hi> by it. Even <hi>little sins</hi> are <hi>great ones</hi> in the eyes of such persons; they do not say, as <hi>Jonathan</hi> did,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 14.43.</note>
               <hi>I have but tasted a little honey
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:40873:39"/>with the end of the rod that was in my hand, and lo I must dye;</hi> but heartily consent and agree to this, that their Damnation is justly inflicted, by whom the least iniquity is knowingly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed. We find,<note place="margin">Gen. 14.23.</note> that <hi>Abraham</hi> would not take <hi>from a thread to a shoo-latchet</hi> of any thing that belonged to the <hi>King of Sodom.</hi> And, when <hi>Pharaoh</hi> yielded, that the people of <hi>Israel</hi> and their little ones should <hi>go and sacrifice to God,</hi> only their <hi>flocks</hi> should be stayed; <hi>Moses</hi> told him, that their cattle also should attend,<note place="margin">Exo. 10.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6.</note> and <hi>not an hoof be left behind.</hi> So far were the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches planted by the Apostles from keeping <hi>the whole</hi> of the abolished <hi>Jewish</hi> Festivals, that <hi>Paul</hi> tells the <hi>Colossians,</hi> that <hi>no man should judge them for part of an holiday.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Col. 2.16.</note> (As the word pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:40873:39"/>imports, though our Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slation renders it with disadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.) One of the <hi>Ancient Church-Historians</hi> tells us of <hi>Marcus, Bishop of Arethusa,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Theo. Hist. Eccl.</hi> l. 3. c. 6.</note> who having destroyed on Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous Grove in <hi>Constantines</hi> time, and afterwards in <hi>Julians</hi> Reign, being prosecuted for it, though they first exercised him with variety of inhumane Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, such as scourging of his naked Body, dragging him thro' the filthiest places, piercing him with sharp-pointed Spears, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>smearing him with Oil and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and hanging him up in the heat of the day in the open Air for Bees and Wasps to fasten on, and at length proposed to him to repair what he had destroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or to furnish, at least, one <hi>half</hi> of the summe, (because they thought that his Poverty could
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:40873:40"/>afford no more) or some <hi>small portion,</hi> what he could; he pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptorily refused, and told them, that it would be as wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a thing to give an <hi>Half-penny</hi> for such a purpose, as to give all that it required.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> A <hi>particular care in bridling the Tongue,</hi> and <hi>setting a watch</hi> against those common unobserved evils, which are es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially incident thereunto. I say, a particular care as to this, shews that the heart is tender; because the Holy Ghost makes it the mark of a <hi>perfect man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am. 3.2.</note>
               <hi>not to offend in word;</hi> and the Tongue, though a single Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">ver. </seg>6</label> is represented as a <hi>world of iniquity;</hi> and though a little Member, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">ver. </seg>8</label> yet a most <hi>unruly evil;</hi> and therefore he that <hi>refrains his Lips,</hi> may be reasonably suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to <hi>take heed to all his other
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:40873:40"/>wayes.</hi> Now this Tenderness concerns six things which are not generally so much minded, as they should be.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Much Speaking.</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Where Words are <hi>few,</hi> Guilt will be the <hi>less. In the multitude of words,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 10.19.</note>
               <hi>there wanteth not sin.</hi> 'Tis a great wonder, if <hi>every part</hi> of over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing Speech should be <hi>season<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with salt,</hi> or if <hi>no idle Words</hi> break forth amongst such a <hi>crowd.</hi> As the very <hi>silence</hi> of the Scripture in many cases is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structive, (for several <hi>negative arguments</hi> drawn from thence have a force in them) so the <hi>holding of our peace</hi> sometimes may conduce to a better <hi>retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our integrity.</hi> How pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently sparing should we be, who are so <hi>apt</hi> to speak irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, and so <hi>unable</hi> to recall it, when 'tis once spoken!</p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:40873:41"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Passionate Raging.</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> How often do the <hi>Mouths</hi> of such as call themselves Christians <hi>fome out their own shame,</hi> to the scandal of Religion, when sinful wrath hath <hi>heated</hi> them! Speaking <hi>fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously</hi> and <hi>unadvisedly,</hi> can be hardly separated. Most are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to think, 'tis a <hi>venial</hi> thing, and ought to be pass'd by, if any unfit expressions do <hi>drop,</hi> because their Passions were <hi>boyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> whereas on the contrary, the <hi>door of their Lips</hi> should have been guarded, because there was a <hi>fire in their Bosoms.</hi> When An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is <hi>broke loose,</hi> our Tongues should be <hi>held in the straiter. So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> deliberately pronounces that sentence,<note place="margin">Prov. 12.16.</note> that <hi>a fools wrath is presently known.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Foolish Jesting.</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> For want of holy Tenderness, this abounds too much in mens ordinary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation.
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:40873:41"/>How many <hi>palpable falshoods</hi> are broacht, how many <hi>prophane,</hi> or <hi>scurrilous,</hi> or <hi>immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest</hi> passages are thrown out, for the venting of a little imaginary <hi>Wit,</hi> and the promoting of a mad sort of <hi>Laughter!</hi> How of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten are men not afraid of abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing the <hi>Sacred Writings</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, by an irreverent <hi>accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation of peculiar Phrases</hi> in them to vain and trifling mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters! <hi>Playing with the sword of the Spirit,</hi> and prostituting the words of the Holy Ghost, and yet crying (with him <hi>that deceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his Neighbour</hi>),<note place="margin">Prov. 26.19.</note>
               <hi>Are we not in sport?</hi> But they who desire and intend that their discourse should be <hi>innocent</hi> as well as <hi>chearful,</hi> will be sure to speak forth none but <hi>the words of truth and sober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> at any time.</p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:40873:42"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Rash Vowing.</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Many persons are very prone <hi>in</hi> some deep di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stress, or instantly <hi>after</hi> some e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent deliverance, to be very liberal in the engaging of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to that which is more than ordinary, and from which they were free before; whereas in a little while, their heat and reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution <hi>cools,</hi> or perhaps the thing vowed proves more <hi>inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent,</hi> and comes nearer to an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possibility, than was at first ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected. Such was <hi>Jephtha's</hi> case; <hi>Whatsoever cometh forth out of the doors of my house to meet me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judg. 11.31.</note>
               <hi>I will offer it up,</hi> &amp;c. and it was his <hi>Daughters</hi> lot to be that Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. The Wise Man warns against this;<note place="margin">Eccl. 5.6.</note>
               <hi>Suffer not thy mouth to cause thy flesh to sin,</hi> &amp;c. The best way is, before <hi>Vows, to make enquiry; i. e.</hi> to consider seriously, what we may war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantably
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:40873:42"/>and willingly perform.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ʋnregarded Promises.</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> It was one branch of an admirable cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter given to a <hi>Reverend Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi> (now with God),<note place="margin">Howe <hi>Fun. Ser.</hi> for Mr. <hi>R. F.</hi> p. 46.</note> that <hi>he was of such punctual fidelity, that his numerous appointments, even in the smallest matters were so sure, that any one might as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly depend upon them, as the constant returns of day and night, unless some extraordinary Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence did intervene.</hi> It is good not to be too <hi>positive</hi> and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptory, in saying, <hi>We will do this or that,</hi> without expressing a due reservation upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of Gods secret pleasure, <hi>if the Lord will:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.19.16.7. Jam. 4.15.</note> As the Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> does frequently; and as the Apostle <hi>James</hi> enjoyns us to do. But when there is plain <hi>insincerity</hi> in the case, that's far worse than an unthought of Hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance;
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:40873:43"/>and upon that score, we see <hi>lavish professions</hi> of the greatest kindness too often expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in <hi>niggardly accomplishments:</hi> Men who take it ill to be <hi>dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trusted</hi> in what they say, take leave to <hi>confute</hi> themselves. Now a Tender Heart, will not suffer a man to <hi>change</hi> or go back, tho' he hath <hi>sworn</hi> never so much <hi>to his own hurt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ps. 15.4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Needless Protestations.</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> He that <hi>feareth an Oath,</hi> will not in his common Language, approach too near to it, without necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. There is a <hi>solemnity</hi> in <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testing,</hi> which must not be made too cheap and vulgar.<note place="margin">Gen. 43.3.</note>
               <hi>The man did solemnly protest to us, ye shall not see my face, except your bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be with you.</hi> So <hi>Josephs bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren</hi> interpreted his form of Speech,<note place="margin">c. 42.15.</note>
               <hi>By the life of Pharaoh,</hi> &amp;c. perhaps this was no more a
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:40873:43"/>
               <hi>swearing</hi> after the fashion of the <hi>Egyptian Court,</hi> (as some have condemned it,) than <hi>Hannahs</hi> phrase to <hi>Eli, Oh my Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 1.26.</note>
               <hi>as thy soul liveth,</hi> &amp;c. And a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Learned Man judges it to be only an <hi>Apprecation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Light-foot</hi>'s Works. Vol. 1. p. 697.</note> or Prayer for <hi>Pharaohs</hi> life; <hi>q. d. So let Pharaoh live,</hi> &amp;c. In short, we ought to be regulated by that Precept of our Saviour; <hi>Let your communication be yea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 5.37</note>
               <hi>yea, and nay, nay; for whatsoever is more than these, cometh of evil.</hi> Not that we are superstitiously tyed to those terms, and to use no other; but the meaning is, that <hi>ordinarily,</hi> a bare <hi>affirming</hi> or <hi>denying</hi> should be lookt upon as sufficient. The most Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entious persons maintain the <hi>cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit</hi> of their Discourse, without any customary Asserverations.</p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:40873:44"/>
            <p> Sixthly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> A <hi>groaning under</hi> the bondage and <hi>burden of remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Corruption.</hi> Where this is <hi>light</hi> and easie, 'tis a very suspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious token, that men are <hi>insen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible.</hi> If we have really reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd our <hi>feeling,</hi> we shall feel <hi>inherent</hi> sin to be <hi>heavier,</hi> as well as apprehend our <hi>actual sins</hi> to be <hi>more, than the sand of the Sea.</hi> Though Satans <hi>strong-holds</hi> are <hi>cast down,</hi> yet the very <hi>ruines</hi> are more grievous and offensive to a spiritual man, than they can be to him that's carnal, while they <hi>stand entire,</hi> and before they are demolished. Saints are more afflicted with the <hi>remnants</hi> of sin, than others are for the uncontrouled <hi>dominion</hi> of it. <hi>Paul</hi> made bitter complaints, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he was brought into a Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate state,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> of his being <hi>sold under sin;</hi> whereas <hi>Ahab</hi> who
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:40873:44"/>
               <hi>sold himself to work wickedness,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings 21.25.</note> being yet unrenewed, complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not at all. A Tender Heart could wish it self <hi>out of the Body</hi> for this reason more than any other, because while it is in the Body, it is so <hi>compassed with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity,</hi> and loaded with an <hi>evil treasure,</hi> which will never be <hi>spent,</hi> till Death comes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire our Souls. A <hi>child of God</hi> is <hi>heavy laden</hi> by carrying only the <hi>rags of the old man</hi> about him, and longs to have the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbrance taken off. He is not afraid of the <hi>compleating of his Sanctification too soon,</hi> (as <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine</hi> while unconverted, when he pray'd for healing Grace, se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly desir'd that he might not have a <hi>speedy Answer</hi>) but he is more apt to fear, that it will be <hi>deferr'd too long; i. e.</hi> Sin is such an irksome Companion, that he
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:40873:45"/>is impatient to be rid of it.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> A <hi>bringing to mind</hi> of former evils with <hi>renewed shame</hi> and <hi>sorrow.</hi> If God hath put within us such a <hi>new Spirit,</hi> as the Text describes, we shall not easily forget <hi>old sins,</hi> tho' already repented of by us, and forgiven by God. The sins which he hath <hi>cast behind his back,</hi> will be <hi>in our sight</hi> still; and though we have escap'd the danger of <hi>future condemnation,</hi> it will not be a desirable thing to us to lose the memory and sense of <hi>past defilements.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 16.63.</note>
               <hi>That thou mayst re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member (sayes God) and be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>when I am pacified towards thee for all that thou hast done.</hi> Indeed we are never so apprehensive of our wretched <hi>unkindness</hi> to God, and of our base <hi>disingenuity</hi> towards him, as when God hath brought us into
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:40873:45"/>a pardoned state. We then see best, what <hi>Bowels</hi> we have <hi>spurn'd against,</hi> and what infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Love we have ungratefully <hi>trampled on;</hi> for the more this <hi>Love is shed abroad in our hearts,</hi> the more is the conviction of our own vileness diffused also. And these penitent <hi>recollections</hi> of sin, after we have had reason to think that they are <hi>remitted,</hi> are the most genuine effects and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain signs of Gospel-tenderness; because then the mind is deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd from its first <hi>horrours,</hi> and yet is not stript of a serious <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morse;</hi> as <hi>Pharaohs Butler</hi> said after his release,<note place="margin">Gen. 41.9.</note> I <hi>remember my faults this day, viz.</hi> the faults for which he had been cast in Prison. <hi>Paul</hi> long after his Conversion did both <hi>blush</hi> and <hi>bleed</hi> afresh (as it were) under the thoughts of former wickedness; he cryes
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:40873:46"/>out,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.9.</note>
               <hi>I am the least of the Apostles not meet to be called an Apostle because I persecuted the Church of God.</hi> Those things which would have been very unfit for any o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thers to <hi>upbraid</hi> him with, he humbly lays to his own charge.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> A chusing rather to <hi>aggravate,</hi> than <hi>extenuate</hi> our own Crimes. As a tender heart wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> prompt us to <hi>confess,</hi> what th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Charity of fellow-Christian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> should incline them to <hi>cover,</hi> so it will make us <hi>heighten</hi> that guil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in our acknowledgments, which other more favourable Judge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ought to make <hi>abatements</hi> fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Though we should not <hi>bear false witness against</hi> our selves, any more than against <hi>our Neighbour,</hi> yet of the two it is much more excusable, and indicates a better disposition, to be too <hi>severe</hi> in self-accusations, than to be too
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:40873:46"/>
               <hi>mild</hi> and <hi>gentle;</hi> to take <hi>more</hi> shame than is indeed due to us, rather than <hi>less. Paul</hi> was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved not to be guilty of that <hi>left hand errour,</hi> and therefore he sets himself in the very upper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most form of Criminals: <hi>Jesus Christ came into the world to save sinners, of whom I am chief.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.15.</note> Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners not yet subdued or soften'd enough, seem willing generally to spare their own Reputation <hi>as much,</hi> and to give God <hi>as little</hi> Glory by Confession, as they can; many times the <hi>half</hi> of what their hearts are privy to, <hi>is not told;</hi> but as <hi>Zophar</hi> speaks of the <hi>secrets of wisdom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 11.6.</note> so we may say of concealed pollutions, that they <hi>are double to that which</hi> does appear, or <hi>is made known.</hi> It is not so where an holy ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derness is wrought; there men are much more prone to <hi>go too
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:40873:47"/>far</hi> in the exposing and censuring of themselves, than to <hi>come short;</hi> that they may be able to say with the Church, <hi>Our confusion covereth us;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 3. ult.</note>
               <hi>q. d.</hi> It is not only spread upon this or that <hi>single part,</hi> but we fall under it <hi>through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out.</hi> Such persons need not to be <hi>painted blacker,</hi> than their <hi>own Tongues</hi> prove them to be.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/>
               <hi>Meekness</hi> under the <hi>sorest Chastisements,</hi> and <hi>thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulness</hi> for the <hi>smallest Comforts.</hi> If the heart be soft, this senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will be <hi>deeply imprinted</hi> on it, and the behaviour will be fram'd accordingly; that <hi>what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever evil we receive from the hands of God, we deserve more and worse; whatsoever good we receive, we deserve not so much, and indeed nothing.</hi> The Church alwayes tasts some <hi>honey</hi> in abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of <hi>gall,</hi> and freely owns
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:40873:47"/>what the <hi>Prophet</hi> declar'd on the behalf of the <hi>Jews</hi> in the time of their Captivity:<note place="margin">Lam. 3.22.</note>
               <hi>It is of the Lords mercies that we are not consumed,</hi> and it is from his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exceptionable <hi>Righteousness</hi> that we are <hi>corrected.</hi> Where sin is a <hi>light thing,</hi> the lightest Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is thought <hi>injurious,</hi> and the weightiest Blessings are lookt upon as <hi>inconsiderable:</hi> Men think that God <hi>deals hardly</hi> with them, if he layes the hand of his Justice upon them <hi>most spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly,</hi> or if he does not open the hand of his Bounty to them <hi>very wide.</hi> On the contrary, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenting Souls <hi>accept</hi> of every Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment <hi>as due,</hi> and of the least Favour as <hi>extraordinary.</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine severities <hi>sink easily</hi> and si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently, like stones that fall into a lap of Wooll; but the <hi>crumbs</hi> which drop from Gods Table,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:40873:48"/>are highly valued. The <hi>penitent Prodigal</hi> does not repine that he had been pincht with <hi>hunger in a far Country,</hi> but was content to be entertained as an <hi>hired servant in his Fathers house.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 15.19.</note> The <hi>least smile</hi> should excite our Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, and the <hi>roughest frown</hi> calls for our Submission. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning <hi>Ephraim bemoned himself,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 31.18.</note> that he had bore the <hi>yoke</hi> with such an <hi>untamed</hi> Spirit.</p>
            <p>Tenthly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/>
               <hi>Abstinence from the very appearances of evil:</hi> This is an Apostolical injunction to be kept alwayes in our eye.<note place="margin">1 Thess. 5.22.</note> So <hi>Moses</hi> tyed up the <hi>Israelites</hi> to the most critical measures of Truth;<note place="margin">Exod. 23.7.</note>
               <hi>Keep thee far from a false matter; q. d.</hi> have nothing to do with that which looks like dissimulation. The <hi>stream</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our honest intentions should run so <hi>clear,</hi> that there may be no
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:40873:48"/>
               <hi>filth at the bottom,</hi> which we are unwilling to have seen at the <hi>top.</hi> The rich <hi>Israelite</hi> was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden to be <hi>as an Ʋsurer</hi> to his poorer Neighbour;<note place="margin">c. 22.25.</note>
               <hi>i. e.</hi> to be guilty of no act, that carries in it so much as the <hi>resemblance</hi> of biting Extortion. The Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> commands his Son <hi>Timothy</hi> to <hi>rebuke the younger women with all purity;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 5.2.</note> implying, that in his whole Discourse and Carriage there should not be the least <hi>sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow</hi> of levity or wantonness. And therefore (as one observes very well) <hi>Titus</hi> is directed to put the <hi>aged women upon teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the young:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 2.4.</note>
               <note place="margin">Capell <hi>of Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.</hi> Part 2. ch. 13. sect. 3.</note> As if it were less advisable to do it <hi>himself,</hi> not only because of the hazard, but scandal, of overmuch familiari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with a different Sex. We know, that <hi>Hamans falling on the bed where Esther was,</hi> was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:40873:49"/>by the King,<note place="margin">Esth. 7.8.</note>
               <hi>as if he would force her;</hi> it had such an <hi>aspect,</hi> though there be little ground to imagine, that it was his <hi>design</hi> at that time. A ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der heart will be accompanied with the <hi>plainest impressions</hi> of Holiness, without so much as the <hi>obscurest shew</hi> of Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness.</p>
            <p>Eleventhly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/>
               <hi>Flying from the occasions of sin,</hi> and incentives to it. He who is as fearful, as he ought to be, of <hi>swallowing the Hook,</hi> will take heed of <hi>playing with the Bait.</hi> When the <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent</hi> first assaulted <hi>Eve,</hi> she made an excellent defence;<note place="margin">Gen. 3.3.</note>
               <hi>Of the fruit of the tree which is in the midst of the garden, God hath said, ye shall not eat of it, neither shall ye touch it, lest ye dye.</hi> We do not read indeed in the <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal prohibition,</hi>
               <note place="margin">c. 2.17.</note> any thing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prest
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:40873:49"/>as to the <hi>touching</hi> of the Fruit, but the woman might ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry reasonably understand <hi>this</hi> to be forbidden, as a step or <hi>intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction towards eating;</hi> for 'tis by no means probable, that she not being yet depraved or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, should knowingly <hi>add</hi> to the Word of God, or mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciously <hi>insinuate the severity</hi> of the Precept. Holy tenderness will keep men at a distance from the ensnaring Temptations, which <hi>lead</hi> to sin. It is a <hi>stain</hi> upon the Righteous Soul of <hi>Lot,</hi> that he chose the <hi>Land of Sodom</hi> for the place of his <hi>abode,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 13.10.</note> upon the account of its pleasantness and fertility, though the <hi>men</hi> were so <hi>exceeding wicked,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">ver. </seg>13</label> and their Neighbourhood so infectious. He suffered for it <hi>twice,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of <hi>Temporals:</hi> (If he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd no injury, as to <hi>Spirituals</hi>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:40873:50"/>also: For who can tell, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his <hi>Drunkenness</hi> might not be learnt from them? <hi>Fulness of Bread</hi> was one of the <hi>iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Sodom,</hi> why not <hi>Excess of Wine?</hi>)<note place="margin">c. 14.12.</note> First, his <hi>Goods were carried away</hi> among the rest, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the <hi>battle of the Kings,</hi> tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> retaken by <hi>Abraham;</hi> and then they were <hi>finally consum'd</hi> in the <hi>destruction of Sodom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">c. 19.17.</note> he being bidden to <hi>escape for his Life</hi> Chast and pious <hi>Joseph</hi> would not hearken to his <hi>Lasciviou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Mistress,</hi>
               <note place="margin">c. 39.10.</note> neither to <hi>lye by her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> nor to <hi>be with her:</hi> He declin'd coming where she was, as much as possible: He did that which she should have done; for <hi>sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ought to have remov'd the allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring object <hi>out of her sight,</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> converst with any of her Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mesticks, rather than him. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> we hold our fingers <hi>too near th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:40873:50"/>flame,</hi> we shall incur the danger of being <hi>burnt.</hi> It is good to be in the <hi>way</hi> of Mercies, and to get out of the <hi>road</hi> of Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, as far as we can. If we would not be stuck with the <hi>poysoned arrow</hi> it self, we should not meddle with the <hi>feathers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Twelfthly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> A very <hi>sober and temperate use of lawful things.</hi> It is fit that our <hi>moderation should be known unto all men</hi> in our greatest visible abundance. They that go to their very <hi>utmost bounds,</hi> are too likely to <hi>run be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond</hi> them; because then there is but <hi>a step</hi> betwixt them and sin. If we <hi>alwayes</hi> take as much freedom as we <hi>may,</hi> it is a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand to one, but that we some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times are transported to take somewhat <hi>more.</hi> If we never <hi>deny</hi> our selves in any measure of that which we might enjoy,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:40873:51"/>we shall find it an harder pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince than otherwise it might be, to <hi>keep our selves unspotted from the world.</hi> Memorials of the mischief of abus'd Prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, should be with us to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strain and regulate our use of it. If there were that <hi>Inscription</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the <hi>Table</hi> in every <hi>House of Feasting,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 8.10, 11.</note>
               <hi>[When thou hast eaten, and art full, then thou shalt bless, and beware that thou forget not the Lord thy God,]</hi> and if the <hi>Guests</hi> were duely awed by it, so as to <hi>feed with fear,</hi> there would not be so many filthy <hi>brutes</hi> oftentimes in the shape of reasonable <hi>men.</hi> Holy <hi>Job</hi> was suspicious of the miscarriage of his <hi>Children</hi> at their merry enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainments, and therefore when those <hi>Festivals</hi> were gone about, <hi>he sent and sanctified them, and offer'd severally</hi> for them all;
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:40873:51"/>because (sayes he) <hi>It may be that my Sons have sinned,</hi> &amp;c.<note place="margin">Job 1.5.</note> There is too great probability of our <hi>exceeding</hi> in such cases, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently it is the more safe and prudent course (which every Tender Heart will chuse) rather to <hi>abridge</hi> our selves of what we are permitted and allowed.</p>
            <p>Moreover, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/>
               <hi>Compassion to the Souls of other men,</hi> is a necessary evidence of holy Tenderness: And this is to be discover'd in several Instances. As,</p>
            <p>Refusing to <hi>make use of the sins of others</hi> for our own advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> If we could save all that we have by another mans <hi>lye,</hi> or <hi>perjury, &amp;c.</hi> we ought not to do it, but to declare and protest a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst it; and whoever silently <hi>permits,</hi> much more, whoever industriously <hi>procures</hi> any thing of that kind, may justly be sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:40873:52"/>to want that Tenderness with which he ought to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued.<note place="margin">Job 13.7.</note> If we must not <hi>lye for God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 3.7.</note> much less should it be done for the serving or securing of a private Interest. It were better that the World should be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy'd, than the <hi>Order</hi> of it lost, which consists in conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to Truth and Righteousness. That which is unlawful <hi>for me</hi> to do, I am not to <hi>put my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon;</hi> for in this I shall act the part of <hi>Satan,</hi> and make his sin <hi>my own,</hi> though I do not <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonally</hi> commit it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Not suffering sin</hi> upon others, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> where we can have any influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to reclaim them from it. How can we see any of our fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-creatures <hi>falling into the fire</hi> of Hell, and <hi>our eye</hi> not <hi>affect our hearts</hi> so far, as to endeavour the <hi>pulling of them out?</hi> How
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:40873:52"/>can we see the Devil <hi>leading cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> so many Souls <hi>at his own will,</hi> and not <hi>muster up all our force</hi> of perswasive Arguments, for the <hi>bringing of them back?</hi> If God do but <hi>hold his peace,</hi> when we are in trouble, and let our <hi>Temporal</hi> Enemies domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neer a while over us uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troul'd, we are ready to cry out, <hi>Where is the sounding of thy bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Isa. 63.15.</note> His <hi>tender Mercies</hi> are quickly call'd into question in such a case: And is there not more reason to doubt of our own, when others are in the hands of more dangerous <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual</hi> Enemies, and we do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing towards the rescuing or freeing of them?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lamenting for</hi> those, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> whom we <hi>cannot reform.</hi> Our Lord set us an example in <hi>weeping over Jerusalem,</hi> because she would
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:40873:53"/>
               <hi>not know in her day the things of her peace.</hi> To <hi>yern over</hi> those miserable sinners, who are <hi>strait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en'd in their own bowels,</hi> and harden'd against themselves, is a sign of Tenderness of Heart. The <hi>Prophet</hi> told the people of the <hi>Jews,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 13.17:</note> that <hi>if they would not hear</hi> his publick Instructions, he should be a private <hi>mourner</hi> for their incorrigibleness. And <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> when he <hi>beheld the trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressours,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 119.158.</note>
               <hi>was grieved</hi> for them. 'Tis real matter of <hi>sorrow</hi> to see men distractedly <hi>merry</hi> in the most desperate circumstances, that will not be brought to themselves; to see a company of Satans Prisoners <hi>in the bonds of iniquity,</hi> that will not accept of the <hi>Liberty</hi> proclaim'd and purchast by the Redeemer. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dealing gently</hi> with those in whom we find any <hi>hopeful dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition</hi>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:40873:53"/>to Repentance. It is one thing to let men alone that have offended, and another thing to treat them, as if we were <hi>glad of the opportunity</hi> to vent our own <hi>pride,</hi> or <hi>envy,</hi> or <hi>wrath</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them. Some take a mighty delight in aggravating and <hi>black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> the sins of others, as if their <hi>Reproach,</hi> rather than their <hi>Reformation,</hi> were the thing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sir'd. <hi>Joseph</hi> used no such rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, when he discover'd himself to his <hi>Brethren,</hi> and they were <hi>troubled at his presence; Be not grieved</hi> (sayes he) <hi>nor angry with your selves</hi> (<hi>i.e.</hi> not immoderate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) <hi>that you sold me hither;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 45.5.</note>
               <hi>for God did send me before you to preserve life.</hi> He comforts them with the goodness of the <hi>event,</hi> when he might have insisted on the foulness of their <hi>crime.</hi> Such as have faulter'd through a <hi>spirit
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:40873:54"/>of infirmity,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6.1.</note> are to be <hi>restored with a spirit of meekness</hi> In such cases we should be as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to load them too much, or censure them too hard, as our Lords <hi>supposed Father,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 1.19</note> was to expose his <hi>real Mother.</hi> As a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable God declares himself <hi>ready to forgive,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ephes. 4.32.</note> so will a <hi>tender hearted</hi> Christian be; much more forward to <hi>heal,</hi> than to <hi>wound,</hi> and to <hi>take in</hi> a Penitent, than <hi>thrust out</hi> a Criminal. Mercy is Gods delight, and if we are like him, it must be ours. <hi>Mark,</hi> who was Nephew to <hi>Barnabas,</hi> had once deserted <hi>Paul,</hi> and the <hi>work</hi> he was engaged in; yet he orders the <hi>Colossians</hi> to <hi>receive him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Colos. 4.10.</note>
               <hi>if he came to them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yielding up any lesser priviledge</hi> of our own, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> for the preventing of a <hi>greater injury</hi> and inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience to another. We are <hi>not
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:40873:54"/>to please our selves,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 15.1, 2.</note>
               <hi>but our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for his good to edification;</hi> though it be some detriment to our selves in an inferiour respect. How much better is it to sacrifice a little <hi>Carnal interest,</hi> than by our rigorous claim, to hinder any <hi>Spiritual good!</hi> What can our <hi>gain</hi> be, to compensate for our Brothers <hi>loss?</hi> Who can reckon him to be truly tender and pitiful, or to have a just sense of the worth of Souls that will not deny himself, as to some sensual inclination, or <hi>secular</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, for the saving of his Brother <hi>eternally?</hi> This is not like the Spirit of <hi>Paul,</hi> who ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times laid aside the exercise of his <hi>lawful power,</hi> to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self more <hi>useful</hi> and <hi>exemplary</hi> to the people.<note place="margin">2 Thess. 3.9.</note> This is not like the Spirit of <hi>Moses,</hi> who when God offered to make him the Head
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:40873:55"/>of a <hi>Great Nation,</hi> if he would cease his <hi>Intercession for Israel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exodus 32.10.</note> regarded their Publick Welfare, more than his Personal Dignity.</p>
            <p>Again, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> A <hi>thank ful receiving of Reproofs</hi> is a token of Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness. <hi>Soft hearts</hi> account the <hi>smitings of righteous men</hi> a more <hi>excellent Oil,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ps. 141.5.</note> than the <hi>smoothest words</hi> of deceitful flatterers. Those <hi>filthy Sepulchres</hi> that love to be <hi>painted,</hi> and <hi>daubed with untemper'd mortar,</hi> do certainly partake of the <hi>hardness of stone.</hi> None affect <hi>pillows under their elbows,</hi> but such as have a mind to <hi>sleep on</hi> in sin. If it be our desire and design to <hi>walk worthy of God,</hi> we shall rejoyce that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one will concern himself so far about us, as to admonish us, when we <hi>walk disorderly.</hi> How absurd is it to be dissatisfied with a <hi>saithful reprover,</hi> unless
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:40873:55"/>we have too much kindness to the <hi>sin reproved?</hi> If the doing of those things which are <hi>plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing to God,</hi> be our real <hi>pleasure,</hi> and the <hi>grieving of his Spirit</hi> the highest <hi>grief</hi> to us, how glad must we be to meet with a Friend that shews us the <hi>errour of our way?</hi> How welcome must his <hi>wounds</hi> be, who acquaints us with the truth of our case, and directs us to the most <hi>safe and speedy cure?</hi> The <hi>Wisdom which is from above</hi> is recommended by this Character among others, that it is <hi>easie to be intreated.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jam. 3.17.</note> When it is an <hi>hard matter</hi> to fasten se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Counsels upon men, or to make them bear some necessary Rebukes, it shews that <hi>Folly is bound up</hi> too much <hi>in their hearts</hi> still. He that would not be told when he <hi>does amiss,</hi> is never likely to <hi>do well.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="98" facs="tcp:40873:56"/>
            <p> In the next place, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> An im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of <hi>those very Conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations to the mortifying</hi> of sin, which others abuse to <hi>cherish</hi> it. Tender hearts are <hi>melted.</hi> with the same Sun, whereby hard hearts are <hi>harden'd more.</hi> The <hi>Goodness of God</hi> encourages o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in their <hi>impenitency,</hi> but <hi>leads them to Repentance.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 2.4, 5.</note> Divine <hi>Patience</hi> tempts others to <hi>go on in their trespasses,</hi> whereas they are invited by it to <hi>break them off, Sparing Mercy</hi> prevails more with them, than <hi>punishing Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice</hi> with the common Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the World. That long-suffering which makes others <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay</hi> their Duty, makes them to apply themselves <hi>more diligently</hi> to it. Wicked men alwayes ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue perversely; <q>If God hath forborn me <hi>hitherto,</hi> I may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume upon it <hi>still,</hi> and so fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:40873:56"/>my old course:</q> Good men argue after a quite contrary manner; <q>Since that God hath been so favourable to <hi>me,</hi> I will be the more zealous to do execution upon <hi>my Lusts.</hi>
               </q> Some turn the Doctrine of <hi>Grace</hi> into a motive to <hi>Lasciviousness;</hi> but a Spirit rightly fram'd, makes use of it as a spur to <hi>Obedience. Paul</hi> mentions the other un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grounded conclusions with great abhorrence;<note place="margin">Rom. 6.1, 2.</note>
               <hi>Shall we continue in sin, that grace may abound? God forbid.</hi> So, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">ver. </seg>15</label>
               <hi>shall we sin because we are not under the law, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der grace? God forbid?</hi> Some apply the <hi>Bloud of Christ</hi> to the <hi>root</hi> of their Corruptions, as if it were intended to keep them <hi>alive,</hi> and make them <hi>fruitful;</hi> and they use the <hi>Cross of Christ</hi> as a <hi>prop</hi> to the Devils Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons; but where the Heart is
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:40873:57"/>duly softened, it will be an <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine</hi> or Instrument to break them down. The thoughts of a Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified Redeemer work genuine Contrition, in those that are <hi>called according to Gods purpose;</hi> where the <hi>Spirit of Grace is poured out,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zeeh. 12.10.</note> men <hi>look upon Christ whom they have pierced, and mourn for him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Lastly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> A <hi>punctual attendance</hi> to the Divine <hi>Rule and Stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard</hi> of all acceptable <hi>Religious Worship.</hi> We have been often urg'd, and do freely own our selves oblig'd, to an exercise of Tenderness, in the case of <hi>Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience to Authority;</hi> but it can be <hi>no sin</hi> to refuse what another can have <hi>no authority</hi> to enjoyn. The charge of <hi>Obstinacy</hi> will not lye against us, till it be first made clear, that the Will of Man must regulate the Service of
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:40873:57"/>God, and that a Creature is Commissioned both to <hi>invent</hi> and <hi>impose</hi> what the Creatour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hall approve, and his Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hippers perform.<note place="margin">Mat. 15.2</note> The <hi>Disciples of Christ transgrest the tradition of the Elders,</hi> and broke an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scriptural Canon of the <hi>Jewish</hi> Church, in <hi>eating Bread with unwashen hands:</hi> Yet our Saviour does expresly vindicate them as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o this point, and pronounces, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat they were <hi>not desiled</hi> by it. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">ver. </seg>20</label> We have been likewise very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arnestly prest, and readily ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge our selves bound to study the <hi>Ʋnity of the Church,</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd to be tender of <hi>tearing</hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ending</hi> it by needless Separati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; but this Advice will be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ound to concern those that <hi>cause <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>livisions and offences,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 16.17.</note> for where such offence is given, as creates <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> necessity of dividing, there
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:40873:58"/>can be no sinful breach of Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty objected. If men apprehend the <hi>terms of Communion</hi> with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to be such, that they must either separate from <hi>them,</hi> or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from the <hi>Rule,</hi> 'tis their manifest Duty to chuse the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer rather than the latter. We are commanded to <hi>live peaceably with all,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12.18.</note>
               <hi>as much as in us lyes:</hi> But we are not commanded to sacrifice <hi>Truth</hi> or <hi>Purity</hi> for Peace. And besides <hi>Peace</hi> may be preserved, though there be an unavoidable <hi>difference</hi> in O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion (and consequently in Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice) through variety of light, so long as persons do only judge for <hi>themselves,</hi> and maintain Christian <hi>Charity</hi> towards those whom they differ from. In short, the <hi>Bible</hi> is the <hi>common measure</hi> which all our Services should be directed by; and i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:40873:58"/>we <hi>behave our selves in the House of God</hi> otherwise then that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>points, we should reckon it a <hi>misbehaziour.</hi> We <hi>rush</hi> too hasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into the Divine Presence, if we do not first seriously ask our own Hearts concerning those particular acts which we go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout,<note place="margin">Isa. 1.12,</note>
               <hi>Who hath required</hi> such <hi>things at our hands?</hi> For to <hi>do</hi> that which God <hi>hath not requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed,</hi> may be as pernicious, as the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaving of what he <hi>hath requir'd, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>sixth</hi> Head, is to open, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VI"/> wherein the <hi>pleasingness</hi> of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oly frame and disposition <hi>to God</hi> does appear. I shall men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on only four <hi>instances</hi> of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uth of it, which as they are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ack'd by the frequent Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce of Gods Servants, will be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ough to prove, that a <hi>Tender
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:40873:59"/>Heart</hi> is most <hi>after his.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>First, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <hi>Audience of Prayer.</hi> God listens more to the <hi>chatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> and <hi>groans</hi> of such persons endued with this gracious tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, than to all the <hi>Rhetorick</hi> and <hi>Eloquence</hi> of other men. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause thou hast humbled thy self, when thou heardest what I spake against this place, and hast wept before me,</hi> (sayes God to <hi>Josiah</hi> here) <hi>I also have heard thee.</hi> When Souls are wrought up to such a <hi>softness</hi> as this, God take<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> notice with great delight of the least expression that <hi>drops</hi> from them. So <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> appear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the <hi>Prophet,</hi> and assures him that <hi>from the first day,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 10.12.</note>
               <hi>that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> begun to chasten himself before his God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Song 2.14.</note>
               <hi>his words were heard.</hi> The <hi>voice</hi> of Gods <hi>mourning Doves</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>sweet</hi> in the Ears of Heaven There is more <hi>harmony</hi> in thos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:40873:59"/>
               <hi>broken sighs</hi> than in the <hi>chiming sound of ten thousands words</hi> that proceed from <hi>feigned Lips.</hi> God <hi>looks to</hi> those that <hi>tremble at his word,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Isa. 66.2.</note> with the highest compla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ency,<note place="margin">Ps. 38.9.</note> and <hi>all their desires are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him.</hi> This is argument e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ough of his peculiar favour to such; for though it be the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on Duty</hi> of all persons to send <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p their Petitions to God, it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot the <hi>common Priviledge</hi> of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o have them graciously receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d. <hi>David</hi> concludes that God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad <hi>not turn'd away his mercy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">—66. ult.</note> because he had <hi>not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rn'd away his prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <hi>Preservation from</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bundance of <hi>guilt</hi> which others <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll into. <hi>Solomon</hi> spake as the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>racles of God,</hi> when he said, <hi>Happy is the man that seareth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ays;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 28.14.</note> for evils which overtake <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s <hi>unawares</hi> are always the worst,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:40873:60"/>and do us the greatest mischief; but the <hi>least danger</hi> is from those that are <hi>most suspected.</hi> When Conscience is <hi>laid wast,</hi> it is the most deplorable state on this side of <hi>Hell:</hi> Men <hi>run away</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all manner of wickedness, like <hi>wild horses</hi> with the <hi>bit in their mouths.</hi> They who are <hi>past feeling,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ephes. 4.19.</note>
               <hi>give themselves over to work all uncleanness with greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness.</hi> We see, that as no <hi>lye,</hi> are too gross to be <hi>believed,</hi> so no <hi>villanies</hi> are too black to be <hi>committed</hi> in the <hi>Roman Church</hi> where their <hi>hearts</hi> (like that o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Leviathan</hi>) <hi>are as firm as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> stone,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 41.24.</note>
               <hi>and hard as a piece of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nether milstone,</hi> [The Holy Ghos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mentions the <hi>nether,</hi> because that being to bear the weight o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>upper,</hi> is usually the solides<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and strongest of the two.] None are so <hi>far from righteousness,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Isa. 46.12</note> as
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:40873:60"/>the <hi>stout-hearted.</hi> Judicial <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uration</hi> is therefore many times <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>poken of in Scripture, as the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orerunner of destruction; this was the greatest <hi>plague</hi> which God sent upon <hi>Pharaoh;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ex. 9.14.</note> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o in the case of <hi>Sihon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 2.30.</note>
               <hi>King of Heshbon, God harden'd his spirit, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd made his heart obstinate,</hi> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e might cut him off. For this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eason, the <hi>Church</hi> makes that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er bitterest complaint, <hi>Oh Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Isa. 63.17.</note>
               <hi>why hast thou made us to err from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hy wayes, and harden'd our hearts from thy fear?</hi> Hardening of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en from <hi>the fear of God,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uces that sad effect of erring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>om <hi>the wayes of God;</hi> and this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> an afflicting token of Divine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nger. On the contrary, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y his fear, we are kept in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ayes, 'tis a mark of his favour:<note place="margin">Josh. 22.31.</note>
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his day we perceive that the Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> among us, because ye have not
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:40873:61"/>committed this trespass against the Lord.</hi> Without doubt, if sin b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the greatest <hi>evil,</hi> the preventio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of it is the greatest act of mercy and <hi>good will.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 22.14.</note>
               <hi>The mouth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> strange women</hi> (sayes the Wise Man) <hi>is a deep pit; he that is abhorred of the Lord, shall fall therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
               <hi>Special protection from</hi> threatening <hi>calamities.</hi> We read that <hi>Jehojakim</hi> and his <hi>Courtier<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> who were <hi>not afraid</hi> at the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the terrible <hi>Roll,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 36.24.</note> felt that Contents of it to their cost;<note place="margin">v. 30, 31.</note> whereas the <hi>Prophet,</hi> who in o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> bedience to God, made Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of <hi>dictating,</hi> and <hi>Baruc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> who <hi>writ</hi> it,<note place="margin">ver. 26.</note> were both shelter'd by Providence. How often have we seen, that they who would not <hi>make lyes their refuge,</hi> have found <hi>refuge in God,</hi> and such as never dared to <hi>hide themselves
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:40873:61"/>under falshood,</hi> have been his <hi>hidden ones,</hi> in a peculiar man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner! When other Hypocrites af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all their base <hi>prostitutions</hi> and forbid <hi>submissions,</hi> have been justly exposed, like the <hi>Court without the Temple,</hi> which was foretold to be <hi>given to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 11.2.</note> How many have deprav'd the Doctrine of Christ, only <hi>left hey should suffer persecution for the Cross of Christ,</hi> and God hath Righteously so order'd the event, that they have fail'd of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention? Men that have aim'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> nothing else, but to be <hi>wise as Serpents,</hi> have been <hi>stung to death</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their own contrivance, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he more <hi>harmless Doves,</hi> and they that were <hi>simple concerning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vil,</hi> have escap'd the <hi>Birds of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rey. Devilish Wisdom</hi> creeping <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nder the name and shadow of <hi>Christian Prudence,</hi> hath done
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:40873:62"/>more mischief to mens <hi>temporal concerns,</hi> than the most are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensive of. <hi>Joseph</hi> was faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to his trust, and kept his <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity,</hi> and fared the better for it at last, though he <hi>suffered a while;</hi> a false accusation threw him into <hi>Prison,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 39.21, 22, 23.</note> but he <hi>Lord was with him, and shewed him mercy, and gave him favour in the sight of his keeper,</hi> who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted all into his hand, and that very confinement made way for his greater advancement in <hi>Pharaohs Court.</hi> The instance of <hi>Mordecai</hi> is rather more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable, who laid open him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, and the whole people of the <hi>Jews</hi> to the rage and malice of <hi>Haman,</hi> a great Courtier and Favourite with <hi>Ahasuerus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Esth. 3.2.</note> by <hi>not bowing,</hi> or <hi>doing reverence to him.</hi> The Reasons of this refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sal, were not either <hi>Pride,</hi> or
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:40873:62"/>
               <hi>Envy</hi> against his particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, or <hi>contempt</hi> of the Royal injunction, but he could not do it upon a Conscientious account; for 1. Many Learned Men do think that the respect requir'd, was not only <hi>Civil,</hi> but <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous;</hi> the <hi>Kings of Persia</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly expecting and receiving no less than <hi>Divine Adoration</hi> from their Subjects, which <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decai,</hi> a <hi>Jew,</hi> had learnt to give to none, but <hi>God only.</hi> 2. This <hi>Haman</hi> was an infamously <hi>wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> man,<note place="margin">c. 7.6. Ps. 15.4.</note> and <hi>as such,</hi> he must needs be <hi>contemned in the eyes</hi> of <hi>Mordecai.</hi> 3. He was by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion an <hi>Amalekite,</hi> of the race of <hi>Agag,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exodus 17.16.</note> who was <hi>hewn in pieces by Samuel,</hi> and God had oblig'd the <hi>Israelites</hi> to oppose that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cursed people in all successive Ages;<note place="margin">Deut. 25.19.</note> so that such <hi>external ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> could not be paid to him
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:40873:63"/>without sin. However this (as I said) was like to have had a very fatal issue; but God sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonably and marvellously inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed; <hi>Hamans plot</hi> was defeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, himself <hi>hanged,</hi> his Estate <hi>confiscated,</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi> delivered, <hi>Mordecai</hi> preferr'd, and they that were to be their <hi>Execution<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> universally cut off.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
               <hi>Comfort in Death.</hi> If <hi>they perish,</hi> yet <hi>their expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> does not; if their <hi>end</hi> seem to be never so Tragical, as to the outward circumstances of it, yet they really <hi>abound in hope.</hi> So this <hi>Josiah</hi> in the Text, was according to the Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise,<note place="margin">ver. 20.</note>
               <hi>gathered to his grave in peace,</hi> though he dyed in <hi>battle,</hi> because he was in a state of <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation</hi> to God, and the <hi>last Enemy</hi> could do him no hurt; for if a good man expire in the
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:40873:63"/>
               <hi>open Field,</hi> and in the midst of the <hi>sounding Trumpets,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>ratling Instruments</hi> of War, yet <hi>his end is peace,</hi> and he <hi>falls asleep</hi> more quietly, than a sinner can do on his <hi>bed of ivory.</hi> This is the more observable, as to <hi>Josiah,</hi> because that <hi>concluding act</hi> of his Life, had something more of blame in it, than any other of his mentioned in the Bible: <hi>He hearkened not unto the words of Necho from the mouth of God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chron. 35.22.</note> It is true, that this pious Prince had no positive ground to believe what the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then King</hi> pretended, but rather might have some reason to mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trust a fallacy; nevertheless, it would have done well, if he had <hi>consulted God</hi> about it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he went to fight; his ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect of doing this, was a <hi>faulty comission,</hi> and his untimely Death
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:40873:64"/>immediately thereupon, may be lookt upon, not only as a <hi>punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> to his people, but a <hi>rebuke</hi> to him: And yet the <hi>light of Gods countenance</hi> shined through those <hi>Evening Clouds,</hi> and after he had his <hi>mortal wound</hi> he went <hi>triumphant</hi> to Heaven. Such <hi>strong Consolations,</hi> when the <hi>flesh is failing</hi> us, are the fullest evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Gods approving us: They whom he <hi>smiles upon</hi> in their dying moments, are his dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings indeed, and his doing it then, will be recompence e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, though he should <hi>frown</hi> upon us all our dayes before. If God <hi>lets his servants depart in peace,</hi> (like old <hi>Simeon</hi>) 'tis a mighty Mercy.</p>
            <p>The <hi>seventh</hi> General, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VII"/> is to give the <hi>Reasons</hi> why this frame of heart does find such accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:40873:64"/>with God. Several things might be alleadged to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose; but the four following are sufficient.</p>
            <p>First, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Because it is a <hi>special fruit of his own Spirit.</hi> God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not take pleasure in any thing that's <hi>ours,</hi> (for all that's <hi>corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>) but that which hath been planted and produced by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, may very well be delightful to him. It is no strange thing for God to pass a sentence of approbation upon his <hi>proper works:</hi> At the finishing of the <hi>Old Creation, Moses</hi> very natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally concludes his account of it with this;<note place="margin">Gen. 1.31.</note>
               <hi>God saw every thing that he had made, and behold it was very good.</hi> But the <hi>New Creation</hi> in every part of it af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords a much more rejoycing prospect to God, both as it is a
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:40873:65"/>glorious conques tof <hi>greater dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties,</hi> and as the issue of it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presses, a <hi>greater conformity</hi> to himself; for the <hi>work of Grace</hi> is not only beset with more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structions, than those of <hi>Nature,</hi> but when it is brought to pass, the Divine Image is more clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be discerned in <hi>it,</hi> than in the best of <hi>them.</hi> This holy dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position therefore being the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar effect of the <hi>operation of God,</hi> is eminently grateful and pleasing to him upon that score.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Because it is a <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguishing Excellency,</hi> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to his <hi>chosen people,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the far greater part of the World is destitute. How few are there comparatively among high or low, that deserve such a <hi>good report,</hi> as is here given to this <hi>King of Judah!</hi> How much cause might we have upon the
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:40873:65"/>scrutiny, to say, as the <hi>Preacher</hi> did, <hi>One man among a thousand have I found!</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 78.28.</note> How little does any such <hi>principle</hi> prevail in the <hi>general practice</hi> of mankind! What is it, that hath met with more Contempt and Reproach, than this very thing, of <hi>Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of Conscience!</hi> As <hi>David</hi> was scorn'd and laught at,<note place="margin">Psal. 69.10.</note>
               <hi>when he wept, and chastened his soul.</hi> How have the odious names of <hi>Peev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ishness, Preciseness,</hi> and a <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitious Ʋnderstanding,</hi> &amp;c. been fasten'd upon it! So far are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny from a diligent <hi>exercising of themselves</hi> to it,<note place="margin">Acts 24.16.</note> (as indeed they should, with the <hi>Apostle Paul,</hi>) that by the <hi>prophanest sort of Drollery,</hi> they have made it their business to discourage it in <hi>others.</hi> But for this very reason, it is the more amiable and lovely in Gods sight, when it appears in
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:40873:66"/>his own Servants; the <hi>less 'tis regarded</hi> by common persons, the <hi>greater esteem</hi> it hath with him. That Holiness which is most <hi>rare,</hi> is most <hi>beautiful; Noah found grace in the eyes of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 6.8, 9.</note> being <hi>perfect in</hi> a very wicked <hi>generation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Because it is the <hi>clearst proof</hi> of a <hi>living state.</hi> How unpleasant Objects must <hi>dead Souls</hi> be to a God that most frequently in Scripture <hi>swears by his Life,</hi> as an Attribute which he chiefly glories in! What Converse or Communion can there be between him, the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Spirits,</hi> and gross and <hi>heavy Carcasses?</hi> (For <hi>stupified</hi> sinners are no better than such.) So far as men are <hi>past feeling</hi> in the matters of Religion, they are truly <hi>void of Life;</hi> when they have lost their <hi>sense</hi> of Sin
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:40873:66"/>and Duty, it shews that they are under the <hi>power of Death.</hi> We conclude things that are insensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, to be inanimate; so we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but suppose, that the <hi>Life of God</hi> is extinct, where all <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual perception</hi> is destroyed. The very first act of Divine <hi>Quicken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> is instantly manifested by this restored faculty of <hi>discerning;</hi> assoon as God hath <hi>breathed upon our dry Bones,</hi> we are that very moment furnished with <hi>Tender Hearts.</hi> But let none who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of <hi>remaining hardness,</hi> rash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly infer from hence, that they are not yet <hi>made alive;</hi> upon these two accounts, remembring that, 1. It is a considerable <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree</hi> of Tenderness, to be <hi>sensible</hi> of Hardness. 2. The more our Tenderness <hi>increases,</hi> the <hi>more sensible</hi> we shall be of the Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness which remains.</p>
            <pb n="120" facs="tcp:40873:67"/>
            <p> Fourthly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Because this temper of Soul is the <hi>highest pitch of sincerity,</hi> and the <hi>nearest approach to sinless perfection.</hi> God will not communicate himself to any but such as <hi>draw hear with a true heart,</hi> and we can have no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter token to <hi>assure our hearts</hi> that they are <hi>true,</hi> than when we find them <hi>tender.</hi> God cannot <hi>be dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleased</hi> with those that are duely <hi>afraid of displeasing</hi> him;<note place="margin">Jer. 5.3.</note> for <hi>his Eyes are upon the Truth,</hi> and where such a fear is, 'tis impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that there should be <hi>prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Hypocrisie.</hi> And them, it is the further step which we can take, towards that perfect Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, which is the priviledge of Heaven; such a constant <hi>suspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion</hi> of sin, and <hi>watchfulness</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst it, is the next remove to <hi>being without it.</hi> No <hi>Militant Saint</hi> is so like to a <hi>Glorified one</hi>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:40873:67"/>as he that <hi>flyes from the least sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow</hi> of evil, which he sees <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suing</hi> him; such an one is the livelyest resemblance of what <hi>himself</hi> shall be, when he comes to <hi>sit down with Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob in the kingdom of God.</hi> So that they who are Singing <hi>before his Throne,</hi> can be but some degrees more acceptable to God, than these that serve him trembling <hi>at his Foot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>eighth</hi> and last thing, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VIII"/> is to <hi>Apply</hi> the whole, which I shall do, in a twofold <hi>Ʋse, viz.</hi> of <hi>Information,</hi> and <hi>Exhortation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>First, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋse. </seg>1</label> By way of <hi>Information;</hi> in these four Branches.</p>
            <p>First, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> We may reasonably in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr from hence, that they who are <hi>least concerned</hi> about Gods displeasure, are the persons that
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:40873:68"/>
               <hi>fall most</hi> under it. The hardened Sinners lot is the <hi>Reverse</hi> of all these good Tidings to the Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-hearted. Such as live after the most secure and regardless manner, are <hi>Vessels of the hottest Wrath;</hi> none so wretched, as they that cry (like <hi>Moses</hi> in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother case),<note place="margin">Num. 11.15.</note>
               <hi>Let me not see my wretchedness;</hi> none so manifest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>past cure,</hi> as they that think themselves safe, when they can <hi>avoid Conviction;</hi> who run from the <hi>clamours</hi> of Conscience, as <hi>Hagar</hi> went at a distance from the <hi>cryes of Ishmael.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 21.16.</note> Men ever <hi>expose themselves so much</hi> to the Indignation of God, as when they labour most industriously to <hi>stifle all apprehensions</hi> of it. Internal checks and admonitions are such a Mercy, as the <hi>crowing of the Cock</hi> was to <hi>Peter;</hi> and such as do not think them so,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:40873:68"/>and improve them accordingly, cannot hope, that there is any <hi>Mercy in store</hi> for them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> It must needs be the <hi>Wisdom</hi> and <hi>Interest of Rulers</hi> to shew favour and encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to <hi>Tender Consciences.</hi> (And it is at this day a <hi>National Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing,</hi> that we have such <hi>over us,</hi> as are really convinc'd of it.) <hi>Magistrates</hi> are the <hi>Ministers of God;</hi> and therefore what is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd by God, should be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanc'd by them. And there is nothing which can be more to their own Advantage. Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or Establishment. What a loss, and dishonour, and danger would it be for a <hi>Prince</hi> to be served by none but those, that have <hi>cast off the fear of God,</hi> and so have <hi>loosened</hi> the principal <hi>bond of their Allegiance</hi> to man! What <hi>confidence</hi> can be put in
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:40873:69"/>those, or what <hi>success</hi> can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from them, who have an Arbitrary Liberty of <hi>doing any thing</hi> which answers their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, or <hi>leaving any thing undone</hi> that's unuseful to themselves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Where the <hi>tyes of Conscience</hi> are most <hi>strictly held,</hi> as the <hi>Presence of God</hi> may be best hoped for to give success to <hi>Publick Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagements,</hi> so the <hi>Trust</hi> which is repos'd, is safest from being <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Whatever <hi>gianful circumstances</hi> any persons are in which do any way <hi>engage</hi> them in the <hi>unavoidable violation of Duty,</hi> 'tis plain from this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, that they are <hi>bound to alter</hi> them; for <hi>holy tenderness</hi> must be maintained, though the <hi>unlawful means of our subsistence</hi> be totally given up. It would do well, if this were considered
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:40873:69"/>before hand by all, in the <hi>choice</hi> of their several <hi>Professions;</hi> but where that <hi>preventive Remedy</hi> hath been omitted, <hi>this</hi> must be applyed afterwards. Some are so strangely <hi>involv'd</hi> among a multitude of <hi>snares,</hi> that it is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutely necessary to <hi>quit the sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> they are in, if they have a mind to be <hi>disentangled:</hi> And it behoves every one to reckon that <hi>employment accursed,</hi> which cannot be followed <hi>without sin;</hi> yea, when a Christian finds it (though but almost) <hi>invincibly difficult to abide with God in his Calling,</hi> 'tis past all controversie, I think, that he ought to <hi>leave</hi> it, and (not to live in <hi>idleness</hi> upon <hi>Alms,</hi> but) to take some other method, which is <hi>more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent,</hi> and less <hi>hazardous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> This will teach us, That those things which might
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:40873:70"/>perhaps have some <hi>landable use</hi> in their <hi>first appointment</hi> and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation, should be <hi>laid aside,</hi> when they come to be <hi>perverted.</hi> The <hi>Brazen Serpent</hi> which when first <hi>made by Moses,</hi> was the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strument</hi> of a wonderful Cure, as well as a <hi>significant Type</hi> of Christ, and after that continued among the people for many years, as a <hi>standing memorial</hi> of the goodness of God; yet in <hi>Hezekiahs</hi> dayes, when it was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bused to <hi>Idolatry,</hi> he is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended for <hi>breaking it in pieces.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kings 18.4.</note> The <hi>Love-Feasts</hi> among the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive <hi>Christians</hi> in the times of the <hi>Apostles,</hi> were originally ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated, for the preservation and increase of mutual <hi>Charity</hi> and <hi>Friendship;</hi> but when at length they became the occasions of notorious <hi>disorder,</hi> (which <hi>Paul</hi> begun to take notice of
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:40873:70"/>among the <hi>Corinthians</hi>) they were justly condemned and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born by the Churches of Christ.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.21, 22.</note> So the <hi>Holy Kiss,</hi> mentioned in several of the <hi>Epistles,</hi> which the Believers were wont to <hi>Greet one another</hi> with, (and which was an ancient custom of <hi>Salutation</hi> practised amongst the <hi>Jews,</hi>) was at last prudently forbidden and disused, in their Sacred <hi>Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies,</hi> when they saw that it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened a door to Lasciviousness. (As indeed <hi>Religious</hi> Affections are too prone to degenerate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Carnal,</hi> and that which <hi>begins in the Spirit,</hi> too often <hi>ends in the Flesh.</hi>)</p>
            <p>Secondly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋse. </seg>2</label> A <hi>word of Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi> which is this; Labour to <hi>obtain</hi> and <hi>preserve</hi> this blessed <hi>frame of Heart,</hi> which is of such <hi>great price in the sight of God.</hi>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:40873:71"/>In order to it, Take the ensuing <hi>Directions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>First, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Strive to <hi>increase in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Knowledge.</hi> Study to fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> your <hi>minds with Light,</hi> if you would have your <hi>hearts</hi> endue with <hi>Tenderness.</hi> God never gives <hi>an heart to percieve,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 29.4.</note> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> where he gives also an <hi>eye to se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> It is observable, that they whss were <hi>past feeling, and gave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves over to a greedy working uncleanness,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ephes. 4.18, 19.</note> (in the place before cited,) <hi>had their understanding darkened, and were alienated from the life of God, through the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that was in them.</hi> Ignoran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and stupidity, are very natura<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> linkt together; and it is to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> expected, that where there<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> most <hi>blindness,</hi> there should <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the greatest <hi>hardness.</hi> The ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> thing, which the <hi>notion</hi> of Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science carries in it, is the <hi>app<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:40873:71"/>of general knowledge to particular actions;</hi> and therefore the <hi>less</hi> we <hi>know,</hi> the <hi>worse</hi> we are like to <hi>do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Make not your Knowledge <hi>useless,</hi> and neglect not the Light which God hath given you, by <hi>taking things upon trust</hi> from other persons. Why hath God furnish you with a <hi>power of seeing,</hi> if he intended, that others should <hi>lead you blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sold?</hi> Wherein is this better, than <hi>groping at noon day,</hi> when we have the advantage of <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting our own steps?</hi> He that receives the dictates of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man, without examination, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay <hi>swallow mortal Poison,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stead of <hi>wholesome Food,</hi> and be <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dged</hi> in the <hi>Chambers of Death</hi> before he is aware. The best and safest course,<note place="margin">1 Thess. 5.21.</note> is to <hi>prove all things.</hi> We are not truly <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:40873:72"/>Christians,</hi> unless we be like the <hi>noble Bereans,</hi> who <hi>searcht the Scriptures of the Old Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> before they would credit the Preaching of the <hi>Apostles</hi> themselves, those Penmen of the <hi>New.</hi> Take heed therefore of being deceiv'd by the plansible <hi>engagements of other,</hi> to bear you harmless before God; there may be something of <hi>Rhetorick</hi> in that way of arguing, but no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of <hi>Reason;</hi> for how can a <hi>Fellow-creature</hi> do this? <hi>Every one must bear his own burden;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6.5.</note> and it is not supposable for <hi>one Soul</hi> to be in <hi>another Souls stead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Let not <hi>Examples sway</hi> you so much as <hi>Precepts.</hi> If <hi>Barnabas</hi> had regarded <hi>Christ Gospel</hi> more then <hi>Peters practice</hi> (which he should have done) he had not been <hi>carried away with Judaizing dissimulation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 2.13.</note> If we
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:40873:72"/>guide our course by <hi>presidents,</hi> instead of <hi>walking according to rule,</hi> Conscience may soon be <hi>shipwrackt.</hi> The <hi>former Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours</hi> who had been before <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Neh. 5.15.</note> were <hi>chargeable</hi> to the people, they had opprest them, and insulted over them, but <hi>so did not he, because of the fear of God.</hi> We must not be frighted and scar'd with the <hi>reproach of singularity; though all men should be offended</hi> in Christ, let us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solve <hi>never to be offended;</hi> but carry our selves like those two <hi>mgighty men</hi> whom <hi>David</hi> had, that stood and opposed the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>listins,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 23.9, 10, 11, 12.</note> when the people of <hi>Israel were gone away and fled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
               <hi>Decline all unneces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary converse with bad men.</hi> The <hi>Jews</hi> would not go into the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick <hi>Judgment-Hall,</hi> when our Lord was arraign'd before <hi>Pilate,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:40873:73"/>lest they should be defiled</hi> by the company of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> which crowded there:<note place="margin">John 18.28.</note> They were jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of a <hi>Ceremonial</hi> defilement, we have more reason to fear a <hi>Moral</hi> pollution by too near ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches to wicked men, when we may easily keep our selves at a distance from them. The Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians were commanded to <hi>hate even the garments spotted with the flesh;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jude 23.</note> and to manifest their ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, by shunning all <hi>familiarity</hi> with such; in allusion to the <hi>Law of Moses,</hi> (as some think), that <hi>whosoever toucht the bed of him that had a running issue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lev. 15.5.</note>
               <hi>was to wash his clothes, and bathe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self in water, and be unclean till the even.</hi> Sad experience may convince of the ruining hazard of accustomed society with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane and carnal persons; if we venture our selves among those,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:40873:73"/>by whom Holiness is mock'd and Herided, we may be too quickly brought to disapprove and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn it also, and to <hi>sit down in the seat of the scornful</hi> with them.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Beware of <hi>laxe inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretations of Scripture-Precepts.</hi> There is so great a <hi>Latitude</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd in some <hi>Practical Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> that to steer by such conduct, would gradually destroy all the enderness, which we are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ssig'd to maintain. Too many <hi>Guides of Souls</hi> have presumed to <hi>widen</hi> Christs <hi>strait Gate,</hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t the hedges</hi> of his <hi>narrow way</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t a <hi>greater distance. Laodicean <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>kewarmness</hi> hath been represent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as no <hi>absolute sin,</hi> but rather <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>f an <hi>indifferent nature</hi> (as if to be <hi>neither hot nor cold,</hi> were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quivalent with <hi>neither good nor bad</hi>), though God threatens it with <hi>spewing out of his mouth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 3.16.</note>
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:40873:74"/>The <hi>third Commandment</hi> hath been expounded to extend to a <hi>forbidding of nothing but Perjury;</hi> which the <hi>vain Swearer</hi> will be glad to catch at. Our Saviours prohibition of <hi>idle words,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 12.36.</note> hath been restrain'd to <hi>malicious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches</hi> of Religion, and the means to confirm it; whereby some may hope the better to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stifie (or at least to excuse) their <hi>foolish talking,</hi> and unprofitable Discourse. I instance only in these things, as a <hi>specimen</hi> of those Doctrines, which are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodated to a very ill pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose; but if we would keep our hearts tender, we must consider the Divine Law as a Rule of the <hi>highest perfection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/>
               <hi>Cherish</hi> the most <hi>vili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying and debasing thoughts of your selves.</hi> They that walk most <hi>hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly,</hi> will walk most <hi>circumspectly
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:40873:74"/>Lowliness of mind</hi> is a great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oter of <hi>Tenderness of heart.</hi> He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat is already <hi>vile in his own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es,</hi> is likely to take the most effectual eare, that he may not <hi>take himself more vile</hi> by sin. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pirit of God speaks of <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>adnezzars mind being harden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in</hi> (or <hi>by) pride.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 5.20.</note> And the <hi>Psalmist</hi> admonishes the <hi>wicked <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ls</hi> of his time,<note place="margin">Ps. 75.5.</note>
               <hi>not to lift up <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eir horn on high, or speak with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>stiff neck.</hi> It is a Metaphor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ken from those <hi>untamed Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>res,</hi> which will not <hi>stoop,</hi> or <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> their heads</hi> to receive the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ke;</hi> so arrogant and <hi>lofty</hi> Souls <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould not be too <hi>straitly</hi> kept <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nder Divine Government, as they thought it their essential <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ght, to take the freedom some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nes of <hi>doing their own pleasure,</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d <hi>walking after their own ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations.</hi>
            </p>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="134" facs="tcp:40873:75"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="135" facs="tcp:40873:75"/>
            <pb n="136" facs="tcp:40873:76"/>
            <p> Seventhly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/>
               <hi>Watch against for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality in Gods Service:</hi> Going on in a <hi>beaten road</hi> of Duties af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a lifeless manner, tends to make the heart like the <hi>way side. Solomon</hi> giving an account of the <hi>Harlot's</hi> assaulting the <hi>young man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 7.13, 14.</note> tells us, that <hi>with an impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent face she said unto him, I have peace-offerings with me, this day I have paid my vows.</hi> It seems, that she had an external <hi>form of Godliness,</hi> and kept up a reputation of Religion by <hi>Temple-worship,</hi> and by doing so, she grew the <hi>more bold</hi> and da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in her wickedness, and <hi>shook off</hi> all that remorse which might otherwise have <hi>siez'd and fasten'd</hi> upon her. This is very evident in the case of the <hi>Jews</hi> during the <hi>Captivity; for seventy years</hi> together they held on a course of <hi>fasting and mourning,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zec. 7.5.</note>
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:40873:76"/>but did <hi>not at all fast unto God,</hi> and the issue of it was, that they <hi>made their hearts as an ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant-stone.</hi>
               <note place="margin">ver. 12.</note> A <hi>superficial dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of Duties</hi> does abundance of harm in <hi>wearing away the sense of sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Eighthly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Take heed of <hi>lying under any guilt unrepented of,</hi> or of <hi>relapsing into sins</hi> whereof you have <hi>formerly repented.</hi> This tends to <hi>brawn</hi> and <hi>sear</hi> the Conscience, and to abate that <hi>quickness</hi> of perception which is our great advantage. It is very remarkable, that <hi>Peters stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and warming himself</hi> among the Servants and Officers in the High-Priests Hall,<note place="margin">John 18.18, 25.</note> after he had <hi>denied</hi> his Master <hi>once,</hi> is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned <hi>twice</hi> by the Holy Ghost; for if instead of doing so, he had <hi>gone out immediately,</hi> and bewail'd his sin (as he did after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards),
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:40873:77"/>he might have escap'd the snare of his <hi>second and third Denials.</hi> Delayes in such cases are alwayes pernicious; this is clearly hinted by the <hi>Apostle; Exhort one another daily, while it is called to day,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 3.13.</note>
               <hi>lest any of you be hardened,</hi> &amp;c. Long <hi>custom</hi> brought some of the believing <hi>Gentiles</hi> to look upon <hi>Fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> as a <hi>thing indifferent,</hi> which makes the <hi>Apostolical Council</hi> at <hi>Jerusalem</hi> to prohibit it among other things <hi>of that kind.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 15.20.</note> And therefore, when <hi>Nehemiah</hi> had rebuk'd the <hi>Nobles</hi> and <hi>Rulers,</hi> for exacting of their poorer Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, he bids them to <hi>restore</hi> to those whom they had so opprest, <hi>their Lands and Houses,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Neh. 5.11.</note> &amp;c. <hi>even this day.</hi> Evasions might have been found out to frustrate his advice, if it were not instantly followed. <hi>Putting off</hi> Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:40873:77"/>and frequent <hi>Back slidings,</hi> corrupt the frame of the heart, and lead to forgetfulness of God.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> Let nothing tempt you to <hi>go against the dictates</hi> of Conscience, or to act with the least <hi>reluctancy and hesitation</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your own Spirits. As in those things, which we <hi>positive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> apprehend to be <hi>sinful,</hi> so where we <hi>cannot satisfie</hi> our selves that they are <hi>lawful,</hi> it behoves us to <hi>suspend</hi> and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear, till we have clearer light and information. They who think and teach, that the <hi>doubts</hi> of private persons are to be <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-rul'd</hi> by the <hi>injunctions</hi> of Superiours, lay down very dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent measurs from the <hi>Apostle; Let every man be fully perswaded in his own mind.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 14.5.</note> And again, <hi>Whatsoever is not of faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">ver. 23.</note>
               <hi>is sin.</hi>
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:40873:78"/>Can we now suppose, that the Spirit of God order'd us to <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiesce</hi> in what another com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, for no other reason, but <hi>because he commands</hi> it, and to <hi>believe</hi> the lawfulness of an Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Prescription, when we cannot personally <hi>discern</hi> it? Does not the <hi>good</hi> and <hi>evil</hi> of our actions remain <hi>unalterable,</hi> and yet must the meer <hi>exercise of power</hi> turn the scale, and be enough to resolve our <hi>Scruples,</hi> of scatter our <hi>Objections?</hi> Can <hi>that alone</hi> settle our perplexed minds, when it is confest, that the <hi>nature of the things</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, is not changed? Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the administring and tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down of such <hi>Opiates</hi> as these, is very disserviceable to real Religion.</p>
            <p>Tenthly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/>
               <hi>Fortifie</hi> your selves against <hi>carnal fear,</hi> and an effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:40873:78"/>sense of <hi>outward danger.</hi> Fix it upon your Souls, that as <hi>Souldiers</hi> of Christ, you are bound to <hi>endure hardness.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.3.</note> Let not a prospect of the <hi>greatest sufferings</hi> terrifie you into the <hi>least complyances.</hi> Indeed they who can support a Profession with outward prosperity, are commonly accounted the <hi>wise in Christ;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.10.</note> but at the end they will appear to be mistaken fools; for the smallest <hi>wound in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> is worse than the sharpest <hi>thorn in the Flesh,</hi> and is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally acknowledg'd so to be, when the <hi>time of healing</hi> is past. Remember, that your business is to <hi>commend your selves to God,</hi> your <hi>Father</hi> in Heaven, though your <hi>Mothers Children</hi> upon though <hi>Brethren hate,</hi> and <hi>cast you out</hi> for his Names sake. It
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:40873:79"/>is a Truth, which long observa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath confirm'd,<note place="margin">Deut. 28.56.</note> that they who are <hi>tender of suffering</hi> (like the <hi>delicate woman</hi>) are for the most part <hi>bold in sinning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Eleventhly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/>
               <hi>Live as under the continual view of God. Set</hi> him <hi>alwayes before you,</hi> who hath said,<note place="margin">Rev. 2.23.</note>
               <hi>All the churches shall know, that I am be, which searcheth the reins and hearts.</hi> He who consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders this seriously, will renounce <hi>the hidden things of dishonesty,</hi> as much as the most gross and palpable Injustice; and when he might make an advantage of anothers <hi>ignorance</hi> or <hi>oversight,</hi> and defraud without discovery or suspicion, he will not do it, He is with-held from <hi>cursing the deaf,</hi> because God <hi>hears,</hi> and from <hi>putting a stumbling block before the blind,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lev. 19.14.</note> because God <hi>sees.</hi> The Holy <hi>Apostle</hi> did not <hi>corrupt
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:40873:79"/>the word of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 2. ult.</note> and adulterate Sacred Truths in his Ministry, as <hi>many</hi> did, because he spoke al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes <hi>as in the sight of God.</hi> And perhaps this may be <hi>one</hi> reason, why <hi>Glorified Saints</hi> in Heaven <hi>can sin no more,</hi> because they are influenc'd so vigorously and effectually by the <hi>full</hi> and <hi>immediate,</hi> and <hi>constant Vision</hi> of God; the removal of <hi>tempting objects from them</hi> is not so much, as the presence of such an <hi>awful object with them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the last place, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/>
               <hi>Pray with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ceasing</hi> for <hi>renewed aids</hi> from God against <hi>every motion of sin,</hi> and <hi>assault of temptation.</hi> It hath been intimated before, that he who <hi>makes</hi> the heart soft <hi>at first,</hi> must <hi>keep</hi> it so <hi>afterwards;</hi> and therefore this <hi>work of Grace</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be better <hi>strengthen'd,</hi> or more prosperously <hi>advanc'd,</hi> than
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:40873:80"/>by <hi>diligent application</hi> of our selves to the <hi>Throne of Grace.</hi> The way to be secur'd from <hi>sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful falls,</hi> is to be <hi>much upon our Knees.</hi> The more we <hi>converse with God</hi> in this Duty, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er <hi>succour</hi> may we <hi>expect from him.</hi> The disufe of this will weaken and endanger us more than any thing besides; it will <hi>slacken</hi> those <hi>restraints</hi> under which our Spirits ought to be <hi>held,</hi> and render us more apt to listen to the <hi>charms</hi> of our own Lust, and to the <hi>proposals</hi> of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan:<note place="margin">2 Chron. 16.8.</note>
               <hi>Asa</hi> conquered an <hi>huge host,</hi> by seeking to God; but was baffled by <hi>less force,</hi> when he trusted too much to Humane assistance. So 'tis frequently seen, that <hi>sleighter temptations</hi> prevail against us, when we think to encounter them <hi>by our selves,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter we have been victorious o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:40873:80"/>stronger Corruptions by <hi>call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon God for help.</hi> If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we would <hi>give no place to the Devil,</hi> nor his Works, 'tis necessary, that we should <hi>give our selves to Prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude all, Let me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech every one that Readeth, not to <hi>receive</hi> this word <hi>in vain,</hi> by <hi>conferring with Flesh and Blood.</hi> If the World do tell you, that the governing of your selves by such <hi>nice</hi> Rules and Methods, will be <hi>vexatious</hi> and <hi>troublesome,</hi> you may be assured of the contrary, from the <hi>faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> Word of God, and the <hi>Seals</hi> which have been <hi>set</hi> to it by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thousands. To that end, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider these two things well, as an <hi>Antidote</hi> against the <hi>Venome,</hi> which others would infuse.</p>
            <pb n="146" facs="tcp:40873:81"/>
            <p> First, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="(1.)"/> That the most <hi>strictly Consciencious</hi> may best expect to have the <hi>sweetest calm</hi> in their own minds. A Conscience most <hi>void of offence,</hi> is thereby enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled and qualified to be most <hi>free from terrour.</hi> The <hi>sorrows</hi> of Saints are therefore in the fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est time alwayes <hi>turned into joys;</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 16.20.</note> and the surest and most <hi>durable</hi> comforts are never too <hi>hastily</hi> obtained. It is beyond all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troversie, that <hi>no peace</hi> for a while, is better than a <hi>false peace</hi> without interruption: <hi>Acute Pains</hi> are much safer than some <hi>stupifying Remedies;</hi> for <hi>present Grief</hi> will make way for <hi>ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lusting Tranquillity.</hi> An <hi>Eminent Person</hi> hath lately given testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to this Truth;<note place="margin">Bish. of <hi>Sarum</hi>'s Serm. at the Fun. of the Lady <hi>Brook.</hi> pag. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Sometimes</hi> (sayes he) <hi>a great Tenderness of Mind, joyned with a deep Sense of Duty, will raise sad reflections
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:40873:81"/>in those, who have the justest cause of rejoycing alwayes in God; but such cloudy thoughts, though they may disquiet them a little, yet have a good effect upon them,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="(2.)"/> They who are <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected</hi> with a sense of guilt, be <hi>lasht</hi> for it afterwards to their <hi>greater torment.</hi> Many sins which we <hi>easily pass over</hi> in the <hi>heat of Temptation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 25.31.</note> are an <hi>offence of heart</hi> to us in our <hi>cooler Thoughts. Darius,</hi> against the convictions of his own mind, was perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by his <hi>Courtiers</hi> to throw <hi>Daniel into the den of Lyons,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 6.18, 19.</note> but he could neither <hi>eat</hi> nor <hi>sleep,</hi> till he fetcht him out. The <hi>longer</hi> 'tis before we recover our feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the worse shall we be stung <hi>at last.</hi> When some of the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians</hi> were surpriz'd by one of <hi>Julians</hi> Artifices to <hi>cast Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kincense
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:40873:82"/>upon his Altars,</hi> and came to review what they had done, and understood, that their Enemies construed it to be a <hi>Renunciation of Christ,</hi> they exprest the utmost <hi>rage against themselves,</hi> (as well as just re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentment of the <hi>Emperors cheat</hi>) and even desired to be <hi>commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the flames.</hi> To shut up the whole, let this dwell upon our minds, that <hi>That Worm</hi> which can <hi>never dye,</hi> will at some time or other, make <hi>all men</hi> wish, that they had been <hi>more Tender,</hi> by way of <hi>prevention.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:40873:82"/>
            <head>Books lately Printed for <hi>John Salusbury,</hi> at the <hi>Rising Sun</hi> near the <hi>Royal Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change</hi> in <hi>Cornhil.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SIX Sermons on several Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions. By <hi>T. Cruso.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Christian Laver:</hi> Or, a Discourse concerning the nature of Participation with, and the necessity of Purification by Christ. By the same Author.</p>
            <p>An end of Doctrinal Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versies, which have lately trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled the Churches by Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Explication, without much Disputing. By <hi>P. Baxter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Mirrour of Divine Love unvail'd; in a Poetical Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrase of the high the mysteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb facs="tcp:40873:83"/>
               <hi>Song of Solomon;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto are added severall other Poems, being Miscellanies and Pindariques. By <hi>Rob. Fleming.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A New Survey of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer.</p>
            <p>A Rational Defence of Non-Conformity, wherein the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Nonconformists is vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated from promoting Popery, and ruining the Church, impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to them by Dr. <hi>Stilling fleet,</hi> Bishop of <hi>Worcester,</hi> &amp;c. By <hi>Gilbert Rule,</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>The Conformists Sayings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Enquiry after Religion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by a Late Gentleman of the <hi>Royal Society.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:40873:83"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>